Book ContentsPrevious Section 0.7 Functions, Choices, and LoopsNext Section 1.1 Starting Up and Winding Down Book Index

1.0 An Overview of Axiom

When we start cataloging the gains in tools sitting on a computer, the benefits of software are amazing. But, if the benefits of software are so great, why do we worry about making it easier -- don't the ends pay for the means? We worry becuase making such software is extraordinarily hard and almost no one can do it -- the detail is exhausting, the creativity required is extreme, the hours of failure upon failure requiring patience and persistence would tax anyone claiming to be sane. Yet we require people with such characteristics be found and employed and employed cheaply.

-- Christopher Alexander

(from Patterns of Software by Richard Gabriel)

Welcome to the Axiom environment for interactive computation and problem solving. Consider this chapter a brief, whirlwind tour of the Axiom world. We introduce you to Axiom's graphics and the Axiom language. Then we give a sampling of the large variety of facilities in the Axiom system, ranging from the various kinds of numbers, to data types (like lists, arrays, and sets) and mathematical objects (like matrices, integrals, and differential equations). We conclude with the discussion of system commands and an interactive ``undo.''

Before embarking on the tour, we need to brief those readers working interactively with Axiom on some details.

Book ContentsPrevious Section 0.7 Functions, Choices, and LoopsNext Section 1.1 Starting Up and Winding Down Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 1.0 An Overview of AxiomNext Section 1.2 Typographic Conventions Book Index

1.1 Starting Up and Winding Down

You need to know how to start the Axiom system and how to stop it. We assume that Axiom has been correctly installed on your machine (as described in another Axiom document).

To begin using Axiom, issue the command axiom to the Axiom operating system shell. axiom @ axiom There is a brief pause, some start-up messages, and then one or more windows appear.

If you are not running Axiom under the X Window System, there is only one window (the console). At the lower left of the screen there is a prompt that prompt looks like

(1) ->

When you want to enter input to Axiom, you do so on the same line after the prompt. The ``1'' in ``(1)'', also called the equation number, is the computation step number and is incremented step number after you enter Axiom statements. Note, however, that a system command such as )clear all may change the step number in other ways. We talk about step numbers more when we discuss system commands and the workspace history facility.

If you are running Axiom under the X Window System, there may be two X Window System windows: the console window (as just described) and the HyperDoc main menu. Hyper@{HyperDoc} HyperDoc is a multiple-window hypertext system that lets you window view Axiom documentation and examples on-line, execute Axiom expressions, and generate graphics. If you are in a graphical windowing environment, it is usually started automatically when Axiom begins. If it is not running, issue )hd to start it. We discuss the basics of HyperDoc in Chapter ugHyper .

To interrupt an Axiom computation, hold down the interrupt Ctrl (control) key and press c. This brings you back to the Axiom prompt.

To exit from Axiom, move to the console window, stopping @{stopping Axiom} type )quit exiting @{exiting Axiom} at the input prompt and press the Enter key. You will probably be prompted with the following message:

Please enter y or yes if you really want to leave the
interactive environment and return to the operating system

You should respond yes, for example, to exit Axiom.

We are purposely vague in describing exactly what your screen looks like or what messages Axiom displays. Axiom runs on a number of different machines, operating systems and window environments, and these differences all affect the physical look of the system. You can also change the way that Axiom behaves via system commands described later in this chapter and in Appendix A. System commands are special commands, like )set, that begin with a closing parenthesis and are used to change your environment. For example, you can set a system variable so that you are not prompted for confirmation when you want to leave Axiom.

1.1.1 Clef

If you are using Axiom under the X Window System, the Clef command line editor Clef command line editor is probably available and installed. With this editor you can recall previous lines with the up and down arrow keys. To move forward and backward on a line, use the right and left arrows. You can use the Insert key to toggle insert mode on or off. When you are in insert mode, the cursor appears as a large block and if you type anything, the characters are inserted into the line without deleting the previous ones.

If you press the Home key, the cursor moves to the beginning of the line and if you press the End key, the cursor moves to the end of the line. Pressing Ctrl-End deletes all the text from the cursor to the end of the line.

Clef also provides Axiom operation name completion for operation name completion a limited set of operations. If you enter a few letters and then press the Tab key, Clef tries to use those letters as the prefix of an Axiom operation name. If a name appears and it is not what you want, press Tab again to see another name.

You are ready to begin your journey into the world of Axiom.

Book Contents Previous Section 1.0 An Overview of AxiomNext Section 1.2 Typographic Conventions Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 3.0 Using HyperDocNext Section 3.2 Key Definitions Book Index

3.1 Headings

Most pages have a standard set of buttons at the top of the page. This is what they mean:

Help
Click on this to get help. The button only appears if there is specific help for the page you are viewing. You can get general help for HyperDoc by clicking the help button on the home page.
Up
Click here to go back one page. By clicking on this button repeatedly, you can go back several pages and then take off in a new direction.
Return
Go back to the home page, that is, the page on which you started. Use HyperDoc to explore, to make forays into new topics. Don't worry about how to get back. HyperDoc remembers where you came from. Just click on this button to return.
Exit
From the root window (the one that is displayed when you start the system) this button leaves the HyperDoc program, and it must be restarted if you want to use it again. From any other HyperDoc window, it just makes that one window go away. You must use this button to get rid of a window. If you use the window manager ``Close'' button, then all of HyperDoc goes away.

The buttons are not displayed if they are not applicable to the page you are viewing. For example, there is no Home button on the top-level menu.

Book Contents Previous Section 3.0 Using HyperDocNext Section 3.2 Key Definitions Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 3.5 Radio Buttons and TogglesNext Section 3.7 Example Pages Book Index

3.6 Search Strings

A search string is used for searching some database. To learn about search strings, we suggest that you bring up the HyperDoc glossary. To do this from the top-level page of HyperDoc:

Click on Reference, bringing up the Axiom Reference page.
Click on Glossary, bringing up the glossary.

The glossary has an input area at its bottom. We review the various kinds of search strings you can enter to search the glossary.

The simplest search string is a word, for example, operation. A word only matches an entry having exactly that spelling. Enter the word operation into the input area above then click on Search. As you can see, operation matches only one entry, namely with operation itself.

Normally matching is insensitive to whether the alphabetic characters of your search string are in uppercase or lowercase. Thus operation and OperAtion both have the same effect. If you prefer that matching be case-sensitive, issue the command set HHyperName mixedCase command to the interpreter.

You will very often want to use the wildcard ``*'' in your search string so as to match multiple entries in the list. The search key ``*'' matches every entry in the list. You can also use ``*'' anywhere within a search string to match an arbitrary substring. Try ``cat*'' for example: enter ``cat*'' into the input area and click on Search. This matches several entries.

You use any number of wildcards in a search string as long as they are not adjacent. Try search strings such as ``*dom*''. As you see, this search string matches ``domain'', ``domain constructor'', ``subdomain'', and so on.

3.6.1 Logical Searches

For more complicated searches, you can use ``and'', ``or'', and ``not'' with basic search strings; write logical expressions using these three operators just as in the Axiom language. For example, domain or package matches the two entries domain and package. Similarly, ``dom* and *con*'' matches ``domain constructor'' and others. Also ``not *a*'' matches every entry that does not contain the letter ``a'' somewhere.

Use parentheses for grouping. For example, ``dom* and (not *con*)'' matches ``domain'' but not ``domain constructor''.

There is no limit to how complex your logical expression can be. For example,

a* or b* or c* or d* or e* and (not *a*)

is a valid expression.

Book Contents Previous Section 3.5 Radio Buttons and TogglesNext Section 3.7 Example Pages Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 3.6 Search StringsNext Section 3.8 X Window Resources for HyperDoc Book Index

3.7 Example Pages

Many pages have Axiom example commands.

Each command has an active ``button'' along the left margin. When you click on this button, the output for the command is ``pasted-in.'' Click again on the button and you see that the pasted-in output disappears.

Maybe you would like to run an example? To do so, just click on any part of its text! When you do, the example line is copied into a new interactive Axiom buffer for this HyperDoc page.

Sometimes one example line cannot be run before you run an earlier one. Don't worry---HyperDoc automatically runs all the necessary lines in the right order!

The new interactive Axiom buffer disappears when you leave HyperDoc. If you want to get rid of it beforehand, use the Cancel button of the X Window manager or issue the Axiom system command )close. close

Book Contents Previous Section 3.6 Search StringsNext Section 3.8 X Window Resources for HyperDoc Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 3.7 Example PagesNext Section 4.0 Input Files and Output StylesBook Index

3.8 X Window Resources for HyperDoc

You can control the appearance of HyperDoc while running under Version 11 HyperDoc X Window System defaults of the X Window System by placing the following resources X Window System in the file .Xdefaults in your home directory. file:.Xdefaults In what follows, font is any valid X11 font name font (for example, Rom14) and color is any valid X11 color color specification (for example, NavyBlue). For more information about fonts and colors, refer to the X Window documentation for your system.

Axiom.hyperdoc.RmFont: font
  This is the standard text font. The default value is Rom14
Axiom.hyperdoc.RmColor: color
  This is the standard text color. The default value is black
Axiom.hyperdoc.ActiveFont: font
  This is the font used for HyperDoc link buttons. The default value is Bld14
Axiom.hyperdoc.ActiveColor: color
  This is the color used for HyperDoc link buttons. The default value is black
Axiom.hyperdoc.AxiomFont: font
  This is the font used for active Axiom commands. The default value is Bld14
Axiom.hyperdoc.AxiomColor: color
  This is the color used for active Axiom commands. The default value is black
Axiom.hyperdoc.BoldFont: font
  This is the font used for bold face. The default value is Bld14
Axiom.hyperdoc.BoldColor: color
  This is the color used for bold face. The default value is black
Axiom.hyperdoc.TtFont: font
  This is the font used for Axiom output in HyperDoc. This font must be fixed-width. The default value is Rom14
Axiom.hyperdoc.TtColor: color
  This is the color used for Axiom output in HyperDoc. The default value is black
Axiom.hyperdoc.EmphasizeFont: font
  This is the font used for italics. The default value is Itl14
Axiom.hyperdoc.EmphasizeColor: color
  This is the color used for italics. The default value is black
Axiom.hyperdoc.InputBackground: color
  This is the color used as the background for input areas. The default value is black
Axiom.hyperdoc.InputForeground: color
  This is the color used as the foreground for input areas. The default value is white
Axiom.hyperdoc.BorderColor: color
  This is the color used for drawing border lines. The default value is black
Axiom.hyperdoc.Background: color
  This is the color used for the background of all windows. The default value is white

Book Contents Previous Section 3.7 Example PagesNext Section 4.0 Input Files and Output StylesBook Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 4.0 Input Files and Output StylesNext Section 4.2 The .axiom.input File Book Index

4.1 Input Files

In this section we explain what an input file is and file:input why you would want to know about it. We discuss where Axiom looks for input files and how you can direct it to look elsewhere. We also show how to read the contents of an input file into the workspace and how to use the history facility to generate an input file from the statements you have entered directly into the workspace.

An input file contains Axiom expressions and system commands. Anything that you can enter directly to Axiom can be put into an input file. This is how you save input functions and expressions that you wish to read into Axiom more than one time.

To read an input file into Axiom, use the )read system command. read For example, you can read a file in a particular directory by issuing

)read /spad/src/input/matrix.input

The ``.input'' is optional; this also works:

)read /spad/src/input/matrix

What happens if you just enter )read matrix.input or even )read matrix? Axiom looks in your current working directory for input files that are not qualified by a directory name. Typically, this directory is the directory from which you invoked Axiom.

To change the current working directory, use the )cd system command. The command )cd by itself shows the current working directory:default for searching directory. cd To change it to file:input:where found the src/input subdirectory for user ``babar'', issue

)cd /u/babar/src/input

Axiom looks first in this directory for an input file. If it is not found, it looks in the system's directories, assuming you meant some input file that was provided with Axiom.

If you have the Axiom history facility turned on (which it is by default), you can save all the lines you have entered into the workspace by entering

)history )write

history )write

Axiom tells you what input file to edit to see your statements. The file is in your home directory or in the directory you specified with cd )cd.

In ugLangBlocks we discuss using indentation in input files to group statements into blocks.

Book Contents Previous Section 4.0 Input Files and Output StylesNext Section 4.2 The .axiom.input File Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 9.91 ZeroDimensionalSolvePackageNext Section 10.1 Drawing Ribbons Interactively Book Index

10.0 Interactive Programming

Programming in the interpreter is easy. So is the use of Axiom's graphics facility. Both are rather flexible and allow you to use them for many interesting applications. However, both require learning some basic ideas and skills.

All graphics examples in the gallery section are either produced directly by interactive commands or by interpreter programs. Four of these programs are introduced here. By the end of this chapter you will know enough about graphics and programming in the interpreter to not only understand all these examples, but to tackle interesting and difficult problems on your own. The appendix on graphics lists all the remaining commands and programs used to create these images.

Book ContentsPrevious Section 9.91 ZeroDimensionalSolvePackageNext Section 10.1 Drawing Ribbons Interactively Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 10.5 A Bouquet of ArrowsNext Section 10.7 Drawing Complex Vector Fields Book Index

10.6 Diversion: When Things Go Wrong

Up to now, if you have typed in all the programs exactly as they are in the book, you have encountered no errors. In practice, however, it is easy to make mistakes. Computers are unforgiving: your program must be letter-for-letter correct or you will encounter some error.

One thing that can go wrong is that you can create a syntactically incorrect program. As pointed out in Diversion 1 the meaning of Axiom programs is affected by indentation.

The Axiom parser will ensure that all parentheses, brackets, and braces balance, and that commas and operators appear in the correct context.

A common mistake is to misspell an identifier or operation name. These are generally easy to spot since the interpreter will tell you the name of the operation together with the type and number of arguments which it is trying to find.

Another mistake is to either to omit an argument or to give too many. Again Axiom will notify you of the offending operation.

Indentation makes your programs more readable. However there are several ways to create a syntactically valid program. A most common problem occurs when a line is indented improperly. If this is a first line of a pile then all the other lines will act as an inner pile to the first line. If it is a line of the pile other than the first line Axiom then thinks that this line is a continuation of the previous line. More frequently than not a syntactically correct expression is created. Almost never however will this be a semantically correct. Only when the program is run will an error be discovered.

Book Contents Previous Section 10.5 A Bouquet of ArrowsNext Section 10.7 Drawing Complex Vector Fields Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 11.0 PackagesNext Section 11.2 Syntax Book Index

11.1 Names, Abbreviations, and File Structure

Each package has a name and an abbreviation. For a package of the complex draw functions from Chapter ugIntProg , we choose the name DrawComplex and abbreviation:constructor abbreviation DRAWCX.An abbreviation can be any string of constructor:abbreviation between two and seven capital letters and digits, beginning with a letter. See ugTypesWritingAbbr for more information. To be sure that you have not chosen a name or abbreviation already used by the system, issue the system command )show for both the name and the abbreviation. show

Once you have named the package and its abbreviation, you can choose any new filename you like with extension `` .spad'' to hold the definition of your package. We choose the name drawpak.spad. If your application involves more than one package, you can put them all in the same file. Axiom assumes no relationship between the name of a library file, and the name or abbreviation of a package.

Near the top of the `` .spad'' file, list all the abbreviations for the packages using )abbrev, each command beginning in column one. Macros giving names to Axiom expressions can also be placed near the top of the file. The macros are only usable from their point of definition until the end of the file.

Consider the definition of DrawComplex in Figure fig-pak-cdraw . After the macro macro definition

S      ==> Segment DoubleFloat

the name S can be used in the file as a shorthand for Segment DoubleFloat.The interpreter also allows macro for macro definitions. The abbreviation command for the package

)abbrev package DRAWCX DrawComplex

is given after the macros (although it could precede them).

Book Contents Previous Section 11.0 PackagesNext Section 11.2 Syntax Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 11.4 CapsulesNext Section 11.6 Compiling Packages Book Index

11.5 Input Files vs. Packages

A good question at this point would be ``Is writing a package more difficult than writing an input file?''

The programs in input files are designed for flexibility and ease-of-use. Axiom can usually work out all of your types as it reads your program and does the computations you request. Let's say that you define a one-argument function without giving its type. When you first apply the function to a value, this value is understood by Axiom as identifying the type for the argument parameter. Most of the time Axiom goes through the body of your function and figures out the target type that you have in mind. Axiom sometimes fails to get it right. Then---and only then---do you need a declaration to tell Axiom what type you want.

Input files are usually written to be read by Axiom---and by you. file:input:vs. package Without suitable documentation and declarations, your input files package:vs. input file are likely incomprehensible to a colleague---and to you some months later!

Packages are designed for legibility, as well as run-time efficiency. There are few new concepts you need to learn to write packages. Rather, you just have to be explicit about types and type conversions. The types of all functions are pre-declared so that Axiom---and the reader--- knows precisely what types of arguments can be passed to and from the functions (certainly you don't want a colleague to guess or to have to work this out from context!). The types of local variables are also declared. Type conversions are explicit, never automatic.There is one exception to this rule: conversions from a subdomain to a domain are automatic. After all, the objects both have the domain as a common type.

In summary, packages are more tedious to write than input files. When writing input files, you can casually go ahead, giving some facts now, leaving others for later. Writing packages requires forethought, care and discipline.

Book Contents Previous Section 11.4 CapsulesNext Section 11.6 Compiling Packages Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 11.10 How Packages WorkNext Section 12.1 Definitions Book Index

12.0 Categories

This chapter unravels the mysteries of categories---what category they are, how they are related to domains and packages, category:constructor how they are defined in Axiom, and how you can extend the constructor:category system to include new categories of your own.

We assume that you have read the introductory material on domains and categories in ugTypesBasicDomainCons . There you learned that the notion of packages covered in the previous chapter are special cases of domains. While this is in fact the case, it is useful here to regard domains as distinct from packages.

Think of a domain as a datatype, a collection of objects (the objects of the domain). From your ``sneak preview'' in the previous chapter, you might conclude that categories are simply named clusters of operations exported by domains. As it turns out, categories have a much deeper meaning. Categories are fundamental to the design of Axiom. They control the interactions between domains and algorithmic packages, and, in fact, between all the components of Axiom.

Categories form hierarchies as shown on the inside cover pages of this book. The inside front-cover pages illustrate the basic algebraic hierarchy of the Axiom programming language. The inside back-cover pages show the hierarchy for data structures.

Think of the category structures of Axiom as a foundation for a city on which superstructures (domains) are built. The algebraic hierarchy, for example, serves as a foundation for constructive mathematical algorithms embedded in the domains of Axiom. Once in place, domains can be constructed, either independently or from one another.

Superstructures are built for quality---domains are compiled into machine code for run-time efficiency. You can extend the foundation in directions beyond the space directly beneath the superstructures, then extend selected superstructures to cover the space. Because of the compilation strategy, changing components of the foundation generally means that the existing superstructures (domains) built on the changed parts of the foundation (categories) have to be rebuilt---that is, recompiled.

Before delving into some of the interesting facts about categories, let's see how you define them in Axiom.

Book ContentsPrevious Section 11.10 How Packages WorkNext Section 12.1 Definitions Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 13.0 DomainsNext Section 13.2 Definitions Book Index

13.1 Domains vs. Packages

Packages are special cases of domains. What is the difference between a package and a domain that is not a package? By definition, there is only one difference: a domain that is not a package has the symbol $ appearing somewhere among the types of its exported operations. The $ denotes ``this domain.'' If the $ appears before the -> in the type of a signature, it means the operation takes an element from the domain as an argument. If it appears after the ->, then the operation returns an element of the domain.

If no exported operations mention $, then evidently there is nothing of interest to do with the objects of the domain. You might then say that a package is a ``boring'' domain! But, as you saw in Chapter ugPackages, packages are a very useful notion indeed. The exported operations of a package depend solely on the parameters to the package constructor and other explicit domains.

To summarize, domain constructors are versatile structures that serve two distinct practical purposes: Those like Polynomial and List describe classes of computational objects; others, like SortPackage, describe packages of useful operations. As in the last chapter, we focus here on the first kind.

Book Contents Previous Section 13.0 DomainsNext Section 13.2 Definitions Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 15.1 Important Things to Read FirstNext Section 15.3 The NAG Library Link Book Index

15.2 The New Axiom Library Compiler

ugWhatsNewAsharp

A new compiler is now available for Axiom. The programming language is referred to as the Aldor, and improves upon the old Axiom language in many ways. The )compile command has been upgraded to be able to invoke the new or old compilers. The language and the compiler are described in the hard-copy documentation which came with your Axiom system.

To ease the chore of upgrading your .spad files (old compiler) to .as files (new compiler), the )compile command has been given a )translate option. This invokes a special version of the old compiler which parses and analyzes your old code and produces augmented code using the new syntax. Please be aware that the translation is not necessarily one hundred percent complete or correct. You should attempt to compile the output with the Aldor compiler and make any necessary corrections.

Book Contents Previous Section 15.1 Important Things to Read FirstNext Section 15.3 The NAG Library Link Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 15.3 The NAG Library LinkNext Section 15.5 Library Book Index

15.4 Interactive Front-end and Language

ugWhatsNewLanguage

The leave keyword has been replaced by the break keyword for compatibility with the new Axiom extension language. See section ugLangLoopsBreak for more information.

Curly braces are no longer used to create sets. Instead, use set followed by a bracketed expression. For example,

set [1,2,3,4]

Curly braces are now used to enclose a block (see section ugLangBlocks for more information). For compatibility, a block can still be enclosed by parentheses as well.

``Free functions'' created by the Aldor compiler can now be loaded and used within the Axiom interpreter. A free function is a library function that is implemented outside a domain or category constructor.

New coercions to and from type Expression have been added. For example, it is now possible to map a polynomial represented as an expression to an appropriate polynomial type.

Various messages have been added or rewritten for clarity.

Book Contents Previous Section 15.3 The NAG Library LinkNext Section 15.5 Library Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 15.5 LibraryNext Section 15.7 Documentation Book Index

15.6 HyperTex

ugWhatsNewHyperDoc

The buttons on the titlebar and scrollbar have been replaced with ones which have a 3D effect. You can change the foreground and background colors of these ``controls'' by including and modifying the following lines in your .Xdefaults file.

Axiom.hyperdoc.ControlBackground: White
Axiom.hyperdoc.ControlForeground: Black

For various reasons, HyperDoc sometimes displays a secondary window. You can control the size and placement of this window by including and modifying the following line in your .Xdefaults file.

Axiom.hyperdoc.FormGeometry: =950x450+100+0

This setting is a standard X Window System geometry specification: you are requesting a window 950 pixels wide by 450 deep and placed in the upper left corner.

Some key definitions have been changed to conform more closely with the CUA guidelines. Press F9 to see the current definitions.

Input boxes (for example, in the Browser) now accept paste-ins from the X Window System. Use the second button to paste in something you have previously copied or cut. An example of how you can use this is that you can paste the type from an Axiom computation into the main Browser input box.

Book Contents Previous Section 15.5 LibraryNext Section 15.7 Documentation Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 15.6 HyperTexNext Section 16.0 Axiom System CommandsBook Index

15.7 Documentation

ugWhatsNewDocumentation

We describe here a few additions to the on-line version of the AXIOM book which you can read with HyperDoc.

A section has been added to the graphics chapter, describing how to build two-dimensional graphs from lists of points. An example is given showing how to read the points from a file. See section ugGraphTwoDbuild for details.

A further section has been added to that same chapter, describing how to add a two-dimensional graph to a viewport which already contains other graphs. See section ugGraphTwoDappend for details.

Chapter 3 and the on-line HyperDoc help have been unified.

An explanation of operation names ending in ``?'' and ``!'' has been added to the first chapter. See the end of the section ugIntroCallFun for details.

An expanded explanation of using predicates has been added to the sixth chapter. See the example involving evenRule in the middle of the section ugUserRules for details.

Documentation for the )compile, )library and )load commands has been greatly changed. This reflects the ability of the )compile to now invoke the Aldor compiler, the impending deletion of the )load command and the new )library command. The )library command replaces )load and is compatible with the compiled output from both the old and new compilers.

Book Contents Previous Section 15.6 HyperTexNext Section 16.0 Axiom System CommandsBook Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.0 Axiom System CommandsNext Section 16.2 )abbreviation Book Index

16.1 Introduction

System commands are used to perform Axiom environment management. Among the commands are those that display what has been defined or computed, set up multiple logical Axiom environments (frames), clear definitions, read files of expressions and commands, show what functions are available, and terminate Axiom.

Some commands are restricted: the commands set userlevel interpreter set userlevel compiler set userlevel development

)set userlevel interpreter
)set userlevel compiler
)set userlevel development

set the user-access level to the three possible choices. All commands are available at development level and the fewest are available at interpreter level. The default user-level is interpreter. user-level In addition to the )set command (discussed in ugSysCmdset ) you can use the HyperDoc settings facility to change the user-level.

Each command listing begins with one or more syntax pattern descriptions plus examples of related commands. The syntax descriptions are intended to be easy to read and do not necessarily represent the most compact way of specifying all possible arguments and options; the descriptions may occasionally be redundant.

All system commands begin with a right parenthesis which should be in the first available column of the input line (that is, immediately after the input prompt, if any). System commands may be issued directly to Axiom or be included in .input files. file:input

A system command argument is a word that directly follows the command name and is not followed or preceded by a right parenthesis. A system command option follows the system command and is directly preceded by a right parenthesis. Options may have arguments: they directly follow the option. This example may make it easier to remember what is an option and what is an argument:

)syscmd arg1 arg2 )opt1 opt1arg1 opt1arg2 )opt2 opt2arg1 ...

In the system command descriptions, optional arguments and options are enclosed in brackets (``['' and ``]''). If an argument or option name is in italics, it is meant to be a variable and must have some actual value substituted for it when the system command call is made. For example, the syntax pattern description

)read fileName [)quietly]

would imply that you must provide an actual file name for fileName but need not use the )quietly option. Thus

)read matrix.input

is a valid instance of the above pattern.

System command names and options may be abbreviated and may be in upper or lower case. The case of actual arguments may be significant, depending on the particular situation (such as in file names). System command names and options may be abbreviated to the minimum number of starting letters so that the name or option is unique. Thus

)s Integer

is not a valid abbreviation for the )set command, because both )set and )show begin with the letter ``s''. Typically, two or three letters are sufficient for disambiguating names. In our descriptions of the commands, we have used no abbreviations for either command names or options.

In some syntax descriptions we use a vertical line ``|'' to indicate that you must specify one of the listed choices. For example, in

)set output fortran on | off

only on and off are acceptable words for following boot. We also sometimes use ``...'' to indicate that additional arguments or options of the listed form are allowed. Finally, in the syntax descriptions we may also list the syntax of related commands.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.0 Axiom System CommandsNext Section 16.2 )abbreviation Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.1 IntroductionNext Section 16.3 )boot Book Index

16.2 )abbreviation

abbreviation

User Level Required: compiler

Command Syntax:

)abbreviation query [nameOrAbbrev]

)abbreviation category abbrev fullname [)quiet]

)abbreviation domain abbrev fullname [)quiet]

)abbreviation package abbrev fullname [)quiet]

)abbreviation remove nameOrAbbrev

Command Description:

This command is used to query, set and remove abbreviations for category, domain and package constructors. Every constructor must have a unique abbreviation. This abbreviation is part of the name of the subdirectory under which the components of the compiled constructor are stored.

Furthermore, by issuing this command you let the system know what file to load automatically if you use a new constructor. Abbreviations must start with a letter and then be followed by up to seven letters or digits. Any letters appearing in the abbreviation must be in uppercase.

When used with the query argument, abbreviation query this command may be used to list the name associated with a particular abbreviation or the abbreviation for a constructor. If no abbreviation or name is given, the names and corresponding abbreviations for all constructors are listed.

The following shows the abbreviation for the constructor List:

)abbreviation query List

The following shows the constructor name corresponding to the abbreviation NNI:

)abbreviation query NNI

The following lists all constructor names and their abbreviations.

)abbreviation query

To add an abbreviation for a constructor, use this command with category, domain or package. abbreviation package abbreviation domain abbreviation category The following add abbreviations to the system for a category, domain and package, respectively:

)abbreviation domain   SET Set
)abbreviation category COMPCAT  ComplexCategory
)abbreviation package  LIST2MAP ListToMap

If the )quiet option is used, no output is displayed from this command. You would normally only define an abbreviation in a library source file. If this command is issued for a constructor that has already been loaded, the constructor will be reloaded next time it is referenced. In particular, you can use this command to force the automatic reloading of constructors.

To remove an abbreviation, the remove argument is used. abbreviation remove This is usually only used to correct a previous command that set an abbreviation for a constructor name. If, in fact, the abbreviation does exist, you are prompted for confirmation of the removal request. Either of the following commands will remove the abbreviation VECTOR2 and the constructor name VectorFunctions2 from the system:

)abbreviation remove VECTOR2
)abbreviation remove VectorFunctions2

Also See: )compile ugSysCmdcompile

Book Contents Previous Section 16.1 IntroductionNext Section 16.3 )boot Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.6 )clearNext Section 16.8 )display Book Index

16.7 )compile

ugSysCmdcompile

compile

User Level Required: compiler

Command Syntax:

)compile

)compile fileName

)compile fileName.as

)compile directory/fileName.as

)compile fileName.ao

)compile directory/fileName.ao

)compile fileName.al

)compile directory/fileName.al

)compile fileName.lsp

)compile directory/fileName.lsp

)compile fileName.spad

)compile directory/fileName.spad

)compile fileName )new

)compile fileName )old

)compile fileName )translate

)compile fileName )quiet

)compile fileName )noquiet

)compile fileName )moreargs

)compile fileName )onlyargs

)compile fileName )break

)compile fileName )nobreak

)compile fileName )library

)compile fileName )nolibrary

)compile fileName )vartrace

)compile fileName )constructor nameOrAbbrev

Command Description:

You use this command to invoke the new Axiom library compiler or the old Axiom system compiler. The )compile system command is actually a combination of Axiom processing and a call to the Aldor compiler. It is performing double-duty, acting as a front-end to both the Aldor compiler and the old Axiom system compiler. (The old Axiom system compiler was written in Lisp and was an integral part of the Axiom environment. The Aldor compiler is written in C and executed by the operating system when called from within Axiom.)

The command compiles files with file extensions .as, .ao and .al with the Aldor compiler and files with file extension .spad with the old Axiom system compiler. It also can compile files with file extension .lsp. These are assumed to be Lisp files genererated by the Aldor compiler. If you omit the file extension, the command looks to see if you have specified the )new or )old option. If you have given one of these options, the corresponding compiler is used. Otherwise, the command first looks in the standard system directories for files with extension .as, .ao and .al and then files with extension .spad. The first file found has the appropriate compiler invoked on it. If the command cannot find a matching file, an error message is displayed and the command terminates.

The )translate option is used to invoke a special version of the old system compiler that will translate a .spad file to a .as file. That is, the .spad file will be parsed and analyzed and a file using the new syntax will be created. By default, the .as file is created in the same directory as the .spad file. If that directory is not writable, the current directory is used. If the current directory is not writable, an error message is given and the command terminates. Note that )translate implies the )old option so the file extension can safely be omitted. If )translate is given, all other options are ignored. Please be aware that the translation is not necessarily one hundred percent complete or correct. You should attempt to compile the output with the Aldor compiler and make any necessary corrections.

We now describe the options for the new Aldor compiler.

The first thing )compile does is look for a source code filename among its arguments. Thus

)compile mycode.as
)compile /u/jones/as/mycode.as
)compile mycode

all invoke )compiler on the file /u/jones/as/mycode.as if the current Axiom working directory is /u/jones/as. (Recall that you can set the working directory via the )cd command. If you don't set it explicitly, it is the directory from which you started Axiom.)

This is frequently all you need to compile your file. This simple command:

Invokes the Aldor compiler and produces Lisp output.
Calls the Lisp compiler if the Aldor compilation was successful.
Uses the )library command to tell Axiom about the contents of your compiled file and arrange to have those contents loaded on demand.

Should you not want the )library command automatically invoked, call )compile with the )nolibrary option. For example,

)compile mycode.as )nolibrary

The general description of Aldor command line arguments is in the Aldor documentation. The default options used by the )compile command can be viewed and set using the )set compiler args Axiom system command. The current defaults are

-O -Fasy -Fao -Flsp -laxiom -Mno-AXL_W_WillObsolete -DAxiom

These options mean:

-O: perform all optimizations,
-Fasy: generate a .asy file,
-Fao: generate a .ao file,
-Flsp: generate a .lsp (Lisp) file, Lisp:code generation
-laxiom: use the axiom library libaxiom.al,
-Mno-AXL_W_WillObsolete: do not display messages about older generated files becoming obsolete, and
-DAxiom: define the global assertion Axiom so that the Aldor libraries for generating stand-alone code are not accidentally used with Axiom.

To supplement these default arguments, use the )moreargs option on )compile. For example,

)compile mycode.as )moreargs "-v"

uses the default arguments and appends the -v (verbose) argument flag. The additional argument specification must be enclosed in double quotes.

To completely replace these default arguments for a particular use of )compile, use the )onlyargs option. For example,

)compile mycode.as )onlyargs "-v -O"

only uses the -v (verbose) and -O (optimize) arguments. The argument specification must be enclosed in double quotes. In this example, Lisp code is not produced and so the compilation output will not be available to Axiom.

To completely replace the default arguments for all calls to )compile within your Axiom session, use )set compiler args. For example, to use the above arguments for all compilations, issue

)set compiler args "-v -O"

Make sure you include the necessary -l and -Y arguments along with those needed for Lisp file creation. As above, the argument specification must be enclosed in double quotes.

By default, the )library system command exposes all domains and categories it processes. This means that the Axiom intepreter will consider those domains and categories when it is trying to resolve a reference to a function. Sometimes domains and categories should not be exposed. For example, a domain may just be used privately by another domain and may not be meant for top-level use. The )library command should still be used, though, so that the code will be loaded on demand. In this case, you should use the )nolibrary option on )compile and the )noexpose option in the )library command. For example,

)compile mycode.as )nolibrary
)library mycode )noexpose

Once you have established your own collection of compiled code, you may find it handy to use the )dir option on the )library command. This causes )library to process all compiled code in the specified directory. For example,

)library )dir /u/jones/as/quantum

You must give an explicit directory after )dir, even if you want all compiled code in the current working directory processed, e.g.

)library )dir .

The )compile command works with several file extensions. We saw above what happens when it is invoked on a file with extension .as. A .ao file is a portable binary compiled version of a .as file, and )compile simply passes the .ao file onto Aldor. The generated Lisp file is compiled and )library is automatically called, just as if you had specified a .as file.

A .al file is an archive file containing .ao files. The archive is created (on Unix systems) with the ar program. When )compile is given a .al file, it creates a directory whose name is based on that of the archive. For example, if you issue

)compile mylib.al

the directory mylib.axldir is created. All members of the archive are unarchived into the directory and )compile is called on each .ao file found. It is your responsibility to remove the directory and its contents, if you choose to do so.

A .lsp file is a Lisp source file, presumably, in our context, generated by Aldor when called with the -Flsp option. When )compile is used with a .lsp file, the Lisp file is compiled and )library is called. You must also have present a .asy generated from the same source file.

The following are descriptions of options for the old system compiler.

You can compile category, domain, and package constructors contained in files with file extension .spad. You can compile individual constructors or every constructor in a file.

The full filename is remembered between invocations of this command and )edit commands. The sequence of commands

)compile matrix.spad
)edit
)compile

will call the compiler, edit, and then call the compiler again on the file matrix.spad. If you do not specify a directory, the working current directory (see ugSysCmdcd ) is searched for the file. If the file is not found, the standard system directories are searched.

If you do not give any options, all constructors within a file are compiled. Each constructor should have an )abbreviation command in the file in which it is defined. We suggest that you place the )abbreviation commands at the top of the file in the order in which the constructors are defined. The list of commands serves as a table of contents for the file. abbreviation

The )library option causes directories containing the compiled code for each constructor to be created in the working current directory. The name of such a directory consists of the constructor abbreviation and the .NRLIB file extension. For example, the directory containing the compiled code for the MATRIX constructor is called MATRIX.NRLIB. The )nolibrary option says that such files should not be created. The default is )library. Note that the semantics of )library and )nolibrary for the new Aldor compiler and for the old system compiler are completely different.

The )vartrace option causes the compiler to generate extra code for the constructor to support conditional tracing of variable assignments. (see ugSysCmdtrace ). Without this option, this code is suppressed and one cannot use the )vars option for the trace command.

The )constructor option is used to specify a particular constructor to compile. All other constructors in the file are ignored. The constructor name or abbreviation follows )constructor. Thus either

)compile matrix.spad )constructor RectangularMatrix

or

)compile matrix.spad )constructor RMATRIX

compiles the RectangularMatrix constructor defined in matrix.spad.

The )break and )nobreak options determine what the old system compiler does when it encounters an error. )break is the default and it indicates that processing should stop at the first error. The value of the )set break variable then controls what happens.

Also See: )abbreviation ugSysCmdabbreviation, )edit ugSysCmdedit, and )library ugSysCmdlibrary.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.6 )clearNext Section 16.8 )display Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.7 )compileNext Section 16.9 )edit Book Index

16.8 )display

ugSysCmddisplay

display

User Level Required: interpreter

Command Syntax:

)display all

)display properties

)display properties all

)display properties [obj1 [obj2 ...]]

)display value all

)display value [obj1 [obj2 ...]]

)display mode all

)display mode [obj1 [obj2 ...]]

)display names

)display operations opName

Command Description:

This command is used to display the contents of the workspace and signatures of functions with a given name.A signature gives the argument and return types of a function.

The command

)display names

lists the names of all user-defined objects in the workspace. This is useful if you do not wish to see everything about the objects and need only be reminded of their names.

The commands

)display all
)display properties
)display properties all

all do the same thing: show the values and types and declared modes of all variables in the workspace. If you have defined functions, their signatures and definitions will also be displayed.

To show all information about a particular variable or user functions, for example, something named d, issue

)display properties d

To just show the value (and the type) of d, issue

)display value d

To just show the declared mode of d, issue

)display mode d

All modemaps for a given operation may be displayed by using )display operations. A modemap is a collection of information about a particular reference to an operation. This includes the types of the arguments and the return value, the location of the implementation and any conditions on the types. The modemap may contain patterns. The following displays the modemaps for the operation complexcomplexComplexCategory:

)d op complex

Also See: )clear ugSysCmdclear, )history ugSysCmdhistory, )set ugSysCmdset, )show ugSysCmdshow, and )what ugSysCmdwhat.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.7 )compileNext Section 16.9 )edit Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.10 )finNext Section 16.12 )help Book Index

16.11 )frame

ugSysCmdframe

frame

User Level Required: interpreter

Command Syntax:

)frame new frameName

)frame drop [frameName]

)frame next

)frame last

)frame names

)frame import frameName [objectName1 [objectName2 ...]]

)set message frame on | off

)set message prompt frame

Command Description:

A frame can be thought of as a logical session within the physical session that you get when you start the system. You can have as many frames as you want, within the limits of your computer's storage, paging space, and so on. Each frame has its own step number, environment and history. You can have a variable named a in one frame and it will have nothing to do with anything that might be called a in any other frame.

Some frames are created by the HyperDoc program and these can have pretty strange names, since they are generated automatically. frame names To find out the names of all frames, issue

)frame names

It will indicate the name of the current frame.

You create a new frame frame new `` quark'' by issuing

)frame new quark

The history facility can be turned on by issuing either )set history on or )history )on. If the history facility is on and you are saving history information in a file rather than in the Axiom environment then a history file with filename quark.axh will be created as you enter commands. If you wish to go back to what you were doing in the frame next `` initial'' frame, use frame last

)frame next

or

)frame last

to cycle through the ring of available frames to get back to `` initial''.

If you want to throw away a frame (say `` quark''), issue

)frame drop quark

If you omit the name, the current frame is dropped. frame drop

If you do use frames with the history facility on and writing to a file, you may want to delete some of the older history files. file:history These are directories, so you may want to issue a command like rm -r quark.axh to the operating system.

You can bring things from another frame by using frame import )frame import. For example, to bring the f and g from the frame `` quark'' to the current frame, issue

)frame import quark f g

If you want everything from the frame `` quark'', issue

)frame import quark

You will be asked to verify that you really want everything.

There are two )set flags set message frame to make it easier to tell where you are.

)set message frame on | off

will print more messages about frames when it is set on. By default, it is off.

)set message prompt frame

will give a prompt set message prompt frame that looks like

initial (1) ->

prompt:with frame name when you start up. In this case, the frame name and step make up the prompt.

Also See: )history ugSysCmdhistory and )set ugSysCmdset.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.10 )finNext Section 16.12 )help Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.12 )helpNext Section 16.14 )library Book Index

16.13 )history

ugSysCmdhistory

history

User Level Required: interpreter

Command Syntax:

)history )on

)history )off

)history )write historyInputFileName

)history )show [n] [both]

)history )save savedHistoryName

)history )restore [savedHistoryName]

)history )reset

)history )change n

)history )memory

)history )file

%

%%(n)

)set history on | off

Command Description:

The history facility within Axiom allows you to restore your environment to that of another session and recall previous computational results. Additional commands allow you to review previous input lines and to create an .input file of the lines typed to file:input Axiom.

Axiom saves your input and output if the history facility is turned on (which is the default). This information is saved if either of

)set history on
)history )on

has been issued. Issuing either

)set history off
)history )off

will discontinue the recording of information. history )on set history on set history off history )off

Whether the facility is disabled or not, the value of % in Axiom always refers to the result of the last computation. If you have not yet entered anything, % evaluates to an object of type Variable('%). The function %% may be used to refer to other previous results if the history facility is enabled. In that case, %%(n) is the output from step n if n > 0. If n < 0, the step is computed relative to the current step. Thus %%(-1) is also the previous step, %%(-2), is the step before that, and so on. If an invalid step number is given, Axiom will signal an error.

The environment information can either be saved in a file or entirely in memory (the default). Each frame (ugSysCmdframe ) has its own history database. When it is kept in a file, some of it may also be kept in memory for efficiency. When the information is saved in a file, the name of the file is of the form FRAME.axh where `` FRAME'' is the name of the current frame. The history file is placed in the current working directory (see ugSysCmdcd ). Note that these history database files are not text files (in fact, they are directories themselves), and so are not in human-readable format.

The options to the )history command are as follows:

)change n
will set the number of steps that are saved in memory to n. This option only has effect when the history data is maintained in a file. If you have issued )history )memory (or not changed the default) there is no need to use )history )change. history )change
)on
will start the recording of information. If the workspace is not empty, you will be asked to confirm this request. If you do so, the workspace will be cleared and history data will begin being saved. You can also turn the facility on by issuing )set history on.
)off
will stop the recording of information. The )history )show command will not work after issuing this command. Note that this command may be issued to save time, as there is some performance penalty paid for saving the environment data. You can also turn the facility off by issuing )set history off.
)file
indicates that history data should be saved in an external file on disk.
)memory
indicates that all history data should be kept in memory rather than saved in a file. Note that if you are computing with very large objects it may not be practical to kept this data in memory.
)reset
will flush the internal list of the most recent workspace calculations so that the data structures may be garbage collected by the underlying Common Lisp system. Like )history )change, this option only has real effect when history data is being saved in a file.
)restore [savedHistoryName]
completely clears the environment and restores it to a saved session, if possible. The )save option below allows you to save a session to a file with a given name. If you had issued )history )save jacobi the command )history )restore jacobi would clear the current workspace and load the contents of the named saved session. If no saved session name is specified, the system looks for a file called last.axh.
)save savedHistoryName
is used to save a snapshot of the environment in a file. This file is placed in the current working directory (see ugSysCmdcd ). Use )history )restore to restore the environment to the state preserved in the file. This option also creates an input file containing all the lines of input since you created the workspace frame (for example, by starting your Axiom session) or last did a )clear all or )clear completely.
)show [n] [both]
can show previous input lines and output results. )show will display up to twenty of the last input lines (fewer if you haven't typed in twenty lines). )show n will display up to n of the last input lines. )show both will display up to five of the last input lines and output results. )show n both will display up to n of the last input lines and output results.
)write historyInputFile
creates an .input file with the input lines typed since the start of the session/frame or the last )clear all or )clear completely. If historyInputFileName does not contain a period (``.'') in the filename, .input is appended to it. For example, )history )write chaos and )history )write chaos.input both write the input lines to a file called chaos.input in your current working directory. If you issued one or more )undo commands, )history )write eliminates all input lines backtracked over as a result of )undo. You can edit this file and then use )read to have Axiom process the contents.

Also See: )frame ugSysCmdframe, )read ugSysCmdread, )set ugSysCmdset, and )undo ugSysCmdundo.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.12 )helpNext Section 16.14 )library Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.13 )historyNext Section 16.15 )lisp Book Index

16.14 )library

ugSysCmdlibrary

library

User Level Required: interpreter

Command Syntax:

)library libName1 [libName2 ...]

)library )dir dirName

)library )only objName1 [objlib2 ...]

)library )noexpose

Command Description:

This command replaces the )load system command that was available in Axiom releases before version 2.0. The )library command makes available to Axiom the compiled objects in the libraries listed.

For example, if you )compile dopler.as in your home directory, issue )library dopler to have Axiom look at the library, determine the category and domain constructors present, update the internal database with various properties of the constructors, and arrange for the constructors to be automatically loaded when needed. If the )noexpose option has not been given, the constructors will be exposed (that is, available) in the current frame.

If you compiled a file with the old system compiler, you will have an NRLIB present, for example, DOPLER.NRLIB, where DOPLER is a constructor abbreviation. The command )library DOPLER will then do the analysis and database updates as above.

To tell the system about all libraries in a directory, use )library )dir dirName where dirName is an explicit directory. You may specify ``.'' as the directory, which means the current directory from which you started the system or the one you set via the )cd command. The directory name is required.

You may only want to tell the system about particular constructors within a library. In this case, use the )only option. The command )library dopler )only Test1 will only cause the Test1 constructor to be analyzed, autoloaded, etc..

Finally, each constructor in a library are usually automatically exposed when the )library command is used. Use the )noexpose option if you not want them exposed. At a later time you can use )set expose add constructor to expose any hidden constructors.

Note for Axiom beta testers: At various times this command was called )local and )with before the name )library became the official name.

Also See: )cd ugSysCmdcd, )compile ugSysCmdcompile, )frame ugSysCmdframe, and )set ugSysCmdset.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.13 )historyNext Section 16.15 )lisp Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.20 )readNext Section 16.22 )show Book Index

16.21 )set

ugSysCmdset

set

User Level Required: interpreter

Command Syntax:

)set

)set label1 [... labelN]

)set label1 [... labelN] newValue

Command Description:

The )set command is used to view or set system variables that control what messages are displayed, the type of output desired, the status of the history facility, the way Axiom user functions are cached, and so on. Since this collection is very large, we will not discuss them here. Rather, we will show how the facility is used. We urge you to explore the )set options to familiarize yourself with how you can modify your Axiom working environment. There is a HyperDoc version of this same facility available from the main HyperDoc menu.

The )set command is command-driven with a menu display. It is tree-structured. To see all top-level nodes, issue )set by itself.

)set

Variables with values have them displayed near the right margin. Subtrees of selections have ``...'' displayed in the value field. For example, there are many kinds of messages, so issue )set message to see the choices.

)set message

The current setting for the variable that displays computation timings:displaying whether computation times timings:displaying are displayed is visible in the menu displayed by the last command. To see more information, issue

)set message time

This shows that time printing is on now. To turn it off, issue

)set message time off

set message time

As noted above, not all settings have so many qualifiers. For example, to change the )quit command to being unprotected (that is, you will not be prompted for verification), you need only issue

)set quit unprotected

set quit unprotected

Also See: )quit ugSysCmdquit.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.20 )readNext Section 16.22 )show Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.25 )systemNext Section 16.27 )undo Book Index

16.26 )trace

ugSysCmdtrace

trace

User Level Required: interpreter

Command Syntax:

)trace

)trace )off

)trace function [options]

)trace constructor [options]

)trace domainOrPackage [options]

where options can be one or more of

)after S-expression

)before S-expression

)break after

)break before

)cond S-expression

)count

)count n

)depth n

)local op1 [... opN]

)nonquietly

)nt

)off

)only listOfDataToDisplay

)ops

)ops op1 [... opN ]

)restore

)stats

)stats reset

)timer

)varbreak

)varbreak var1 [... varN ]

)vars

)vars var1 [... varN ]

)within executingFunction

Command Description:

This command is used to trace the execution of functions that make up the Axiom system, functions defined by users, and functions from the system library. Almost all options are available for each type of function but exceptions will be noted below.

To list all functions, constructors, domains and packages that are traced, simply issue

)trace

To untrace everything that is traced, issue

)trace )off

When a function is traced, the default system action is to display the arguments to the function and the return value when the function is exited. Note that if a function is left via an action such as a THROW, no return value will be displayed. Also, optimization of tail recursion may decrease the number of times a function is actually invoked and so may cause less trace information to be displayed. Other information can be displayed or collected when a function is traced and this is controlled by the various options. Most options will be of interest only to Axiom system developers. If a domain or package is traced, the default action is to trace all functions exported.

Individual interpreter, lisp or boot functions can be traced by listing their names after )trace. Any options that are present must follow the functions to be traced.

)trace f

traces the function f. To untrace f, issue

)trace f )off

Note that if a function name contains a special character, it will be necessary to escape the character with an underscore

)trace _/D_,1

To trace all domains or packages that are or will be created from a particular constructor, give the constructor name or abbreviation after )trace.

)trace MATRIX
)trace List Integer

The first command traces all domains currently instantiated with Matrix. If additional domains are instantiated with this constructor (for example, if you have used Matrix(Integer) and Matrix(Float)), they will be automatically traced. The second command traces List(Integer). It is possible to trace individual functions in a domain or package. See the )ops option below.

The following are the general options for the )trace command.

)break after
causes a Common Lisp break loop to be entered after exiting the traced function.
)break before
causes a Common Lisp break loop to be entered before entering the traced function.
)break
is the same as )break before.
)count
causes the system to keep a count of the number of times the traced function is entered. The total can be displayed with )trace )stats and cleared with )trace )stats reset.
)count n
causes information about the traced function to be displayed for the first n executions. After the n-th execution, the function is untraced.
)depth n
causes trace information to be shown for only n levels of recursion of the traced function. The command

)trace fib )depth 10

will cause the display of only 10 levels of trace information for the recursive execution of a user function fib.
)math
causes the function arguments and return value to be displayed in the Axiom monospace two-dimensional math format.
)nonquietly
causes the display of additional messages when a function is traced.
)nt
This suppresses all normal trace information. This option is useful if the )count or )timer options are used and you are interested in the statistics but not the function calling information.
)off
causes untracing of all or specific functions. Without an argument, all functions, constructors, domains and packages are untraced. Otherwise, the given functions and other objects are untraced. To immediately retrace the untraced functions, issue )trace )restore.
)only listOfDataToDisplay
causes only specific trace information to be shown. The items are listed by using the following abbreviations:

a
display all arguments
v
display return value
1
display first argument
2
display second argument
15
display the 15th argument, and so on

)restore
causes the last untraced functions to be retraced. If additional options are present, they are added to those previously in effect.
)stats
causes the display of statistics collected by the use of the )count and )timer options.
)stats reset
resets to 0 the statistics collected by the use of the )count and )timer options.
)timer
causes the system to keep a count of execution times for the traced function. The total can be displayed with )trace )stats and cleared with )trace )stats reset.
)varbreak var1 [... varN]
causes a Common Lisp break loop to be entered after the assignment to any of the listed variables in the traced function.
)vars
causes the display of the value of any variable after it is assigned in the traced function. Note that library code must have been compiled (see ugSysCmdcompile ) using the )vartrace option in order to support this option.
)vars var1 [... varN]
causes the display of the value of any of the specified variables after they are assigned in the traced function. Note that library code must have been compiled (see ugSysCmdcompile ) using the )vartrace option in order to support this option.
)within executingFunction
causes the display of trace information only if the traced function is called when the given executingFunction is running.

The following are the options for tracing constructors, domains and packages.

)local [op1 [... opN]]
causes local functions of the constructor to be traced. Note that to untrace an individual local function, you must use the fully qualified internal name, using the escape character _ before the semicolon.

)trace FRAC )local
)trace FRAC_;cancelGcd )off

)ops op1 [... opN]
By default, all operations from a domain or package are traced when the domain or package is traced. This option allows you to specify that only particular operations should be traced. The command

)trace Integer )ops min max _+ _-

traces four operations from the domain Integer. Since + and - are special characters, it is necessary to escape them with an underscore.

Also See: )boot ugSysCmdboot, )lisp ugSysCmdlisp, and )ltrace ugSysCmdltrace.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.25 )systemNext Section 16.27 )undo Book Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 16.27 )undoNext Section 17.1 Axiom CategoriesBook Index

16.28 )what

ugSysCmdwhat

what

User Level Required: interpreter

Command Syntax:

)what categories pattern1 [pattern2 ...]

)what commands pattern1 [pattern2 ...]

)what domains pattern1 [pattern2 ...]

)what operations pattern1 [pattern2 ...]

)what packages pattern1 [pattern2 ...]

)what synonym pattern1 [pattern2 ...]

)what things pattern1 [pattern2 ...]

)apropos pattern1 [pattern2 ...]

Command Description:

This command is used to display lists of things in the system. The patterns are all strings and, if present, restrict the contents of the lists. Only those items that contain one or more of the strings as substrings are displayed. For example,

)what synonym

displays all command synonyms,

)what synonym ver

displays all command synonyms containing the substring ``ver'',

)what synonym ver pr

displays all command synonyms containing the substring ``ver'' or the substring ``pr''. Output similar to the following will be displayed

---------------- System Command Synonyms -----------------

user-defined synonyms satisfying patterns:
      ver pr

  )apr ........................... )what things
  )apropos ....................... )what things
  )prompt ........................ )set message prompt
  )version ....................... )lisp *yearweek*

Several other things can be listed with the )what command:

categories
displays a list of category constructors. what categories
commands
displays a list of system commands available at your user-level. what commands Your user-level user-level is set via the )set userlevel command. set userlevel To get a description of a particular command, such as ``)what'', issue )help what.
domains
displays a list of domain constructors. what domains
operations
displays a list of operations in the system library. what operations It is recommended that you qualify this command with one or more patterns, as there are thousands of operations available. For example, say you are looking for functions that involve computation of eigenvalues. To find their names, try )what operations eig. A rather large list of operations is loaded into the workspace when this command is first issued. This list will be deleted when you clear the workspace via )clear all or )clear completely. It will be re-created if it is needed again.
packages
displays a list of package constructors. what packages
synonym
lists system command synonyms. what synonym
things
displays all of the above types for items containing what things the pattern strings as substrings. The command synonym )apropos is equivalent to apropos )what things.

Also See: )display ugSysCmddisplay, )set ugSysCmdset, and )show ugSysCmdshow.

Book Contents Previous Section 16.27 )undoNext Section 17.1 Axiom CategoriesBook Index

Book ContentsPrevious Section 17.1 Axiom CategoriesNext Section 19.1 Axiom PackagesBook Index

18.1 Axiom Domains

This is a listing of all domains in the Axiom library at the time this book was produced. Use the Browse facility (described in Chapter ugBrowse ) to get more information about these constructors.

This sample entry will help you read the following table:

DomainName{DomainAbbreviation}:{ Category1 ... CategoryN}with { op1... opM}

where

DomainName | is the full domain name, e.g., Integer.
DomainAbbreviation | is the domain abbreviation, e.g., INT.
Categoryi | is a category to which the domain belongs.
opj | is an operation exported by the domain.

Abbreviation: | ALGSC
Full name: | AlgebraGivenByStructuralConstants
Belongs to: | FramedNonAssociativeAlgebra LeftModule
Operations: | 0 * ** + - = JacobiIdentity? JordanAlgebra? alternative? antiAssociative? antiCommutative? antiCommutator apply associative? associator associatorDependence basis coerce commutative? commutator conditionsForIdempotents convert coordinates elt flexible? jordanAdmissible? leftAlternative? leftCharacteristicPolynomial leftDiscriminant leftMinimalPolynomial leftNorm leftPower leftRankPolynomial leftRecip leftRegularRepresentation leftTrace leftTraceMatrix leftUnit leftUnits lieAdmissible? lieAlgebra? noncommutativeJordanAlgebra? plenaryPower powerAssociative? rank recip represents rightAlternative? rightCharacteristicPolynomial rightDiscriminant rightMinimalPolynomial rightNorm rightPower rightRankPolynomial rightRecip rightRegularRepresentation rightTrace rightTraceMatrix rightUnit rightUnits someBasis structuralConstants unit zero?

Abbreviation: | ALGFF
Full name: | AlgebraicFunctionField
Belongs to: | FunctionFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D absolutelyIrreducible? associates? basis branchPoint? branchPointAtInfinity? characteristic characteristicPolynomial charthRoot coerce complementaryBasis convert coordinates definingPolynomial derivationCoordinates differentiate discriminant divide elt euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor gcd generator genus integral? integralAtInfinity? integralBasis integralBasisAtInfinity integralCoordinates integralDerivationMatrix integralMatrix integralMatrixAtInfinity integralRepresents inv inverseIntegralMatrix inverseIntegralMatrixAtInfinity knownInfBasis lcm lift minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nonSingularModel norm normalizeAtInfinity numberOfComponents one? prime? primitivePart principalIdeal quo ramified? ramifiedAtInfinity? rank rationalPoint? rationalPoints recip reduce reduceBasisAtInfinity reducedSystem regularRepresentation rem represents retract retractIfCan singular? singularAtInfinity? sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart trace traceMatrix unit? unitCanonical unitNormal yCoordinates zero?

Abbreviation: | AN
Full name: | AlgebraicNumber
Belongs to: | AlgebraicallyClosedField CharacteristicZero ConvertibleTo DifferentialRing ExpressionSpace LinearlyExplicitRingOver RealConstant RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? belong? box characteristic coerce convert definingPolynomial denom differentiate distribute divide elt euclideanSize eval expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor freeOf? gcd height inv is? kernel kernels lcm mainKernel map max min minPoly multiEuclidean nthRoot numer one? operator operators paren prime? principalIdeal quo recip reduce reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan rootOf rootsOf sizeLess? sqrt squareFree squareFreePart subst tower unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero? zeroOf zerosOf

Abbreviation: | ANON
Full name: | AnonymousFunction
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce

Abbreviation: | ANTISYM
Full name: | AntiSymm
Belongs to: | LeftAlgebra RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = characteristic coefficient coerce degree exp generator homogeneous? leadingBasisTerm leadingCoefficient map one? recip reductum retract retractIfCan retractable? zero?

Abbreviation: | ANY
Full name: | Any
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = any coerce domain domainOf obj objectOf showTypeInOutput

Abbreviation: | ASTACK
Full name: | ArrayStack
Belongs to: | StackAggregate
Operations: | # = any? arrayStack bag coerce copy count depth empty empty? eq? every? extract! insert! inspect less? map map! member? members more? parts pop! push! size? top

Abbreviation: | JORDAN
Full name: | AssociatedJordanAlgebra
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo FiniteRankNonAssociativeAlgebra FramedNonAssociativeAlgebra NonAssociativeAlgebra
Operations: | 0 * ** + - = JacobiIdentity? JordanAlgebra? alternative? antiAssociative? antiCommutative? antiCommutator apply associative? associator associatorDependence basis coerce commutative? commutator conditionsForIdempotents convert coordinates elt flexible? jordanAdmissible? leftAlternative? leftCharacteristicPolynomial leftDiscriminant leftMinimalPolynomial leftNorm leftPower leftRankPolynomial leftRecip leftRegularRepresentation leftTrace leftTraceMatrix leftUnit leftUnits lieAdmissible? lieAlgebra? noncommutativeJordanAlgebra? plenaryPower powerAssociative? rank recip represents rightAlternative? rightCharacteristicPolynomial rightDiscriminant rightMinimalPolynomial rightNorm rightPower rightRankPolynomial rightRecip rightRegularRepresentation rightTrace rightTraceMatrix rightUnit rightUnits someBasis structuralConstants unit zero?

Abbreviation: | LIE
Full name: | AssociatedLieAlgebra
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo FiniteRankNonAssociativeAlgebra FramedNonAssociativeAlgebra NonAssociativeAlgebra
Operations: | 0 * ** + - = JacobiIdentity? JordanAlgebra? alternative? antiAssociative? antiCommutative? antiCommutator apply associative? associator associatorDependence basis coerce commutative? commutator conditionsForIdempotents convert coordinates elt flexible? jordanAdmissible? leftAlternative? leftCharacteristicPolynomial leftDiscriminant leftMinimalPolynomial leftNorm leftPower leftRankPolynomial leftRecip leftRegularRepresentation leftTrace leftTraceMatrix leftUnit leftUnits lieAdmissible? lieAlgebra? noncommutativeJordanAlgebra? plenaryPower powerAssociative? rank recip represents rightAlternative? rightCharacteristicPolynomial rightDiscriminant rightMinimalPolynomial rightNorm rightPower rightRankPolynomial rightRecip rightRegularRepresentation rightTrace rightTraceMatrix rightUnit rightUnits someBasis structuralConstants unit zero?

Abbreviation: | ALIST
Full name: | AssociationList
Belongs to: | AssociationListAggregate
Operations: | # = any? assoc bag child? children coerce concat concat! construct copy copyInto! count cycleEntry cycleLength cycleSplit! cycleTail cyclic? delete delete! dictionary distance elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? explicitlyFinite? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert insert! inspect key? keys last leaf? less? list map map! maxIndex member? members merge merge! minIndex more? new node? nodes parts position possiblyInfinite? qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates removeDuplicates! rest reverse reverse! search second select select! setchildren! setelt setfirst! setlast! setrest! setvalue! size? sort sort! sorted? split! swap! table tail third value

Abbreviation: | BBTREE
Full name: | BalancedBinaryTree
Belongs to: | BinaryTreeCategory
Operations: | # = any? balancedBinaryTree children coerce copy count cyclic? elt empty empty? eq? every? leaf? leaves left less? map map! mapDown! mapUp! member? members more? node node? nodes parts right setchildren! setelt setleaves! setleft! setright! setvalue! size? value

Abbreviation: | BPADIC
Full name: | BalancedPAdicInteger
Belongs to: | PAdicIntegerCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = approximate associates? characteristic coerce complete digits divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extend extendedEuclidean gcd lcm moduloP modulus multiEuclidean one? order principalIdeal quo quotientByP recip rem sizeLess? sqrt unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | BPADICRT
Full name: | BalancedPAdicRational
Belongs to: | QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D approximate associates? characteristic coerce continuedFraction denom denominator differentiate divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor fractionPart gcd inv lcm map multiEuclidean numer numerator one? prime? principalIdeal quo recip reducedSystem rem removeZeroes retract retractIfCan sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | BOP
Full name: | BasicOperator
Belongs to: | OrderedSet
Operations: | < = arity assert coerce comparison copy deleteProperty! display equality has? input is? max min name nary? nullary? operator properties property setProperties setProperty unary? weight

Abbreviation: | BINARY
Full name: | BinaryExpansion
Belongs to: | QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs associates? binary ceiling characteristic coerce convert denom denominator differentiate divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor floor fractionPart gcd init inv lcm map max min multiEuclidean negative? nextItem numer numerator one? patternMatch positive? prime? principalIdeal quo random recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan sign sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | BSTREE
Full name: | BinarySearchTree
Belongs to: | BinaryTreeCategory
Operations: | # = any? binarySearchTree children coerce copy count cyclic? elt empty empty? eq? every? insert! insertRoot! leaf? leaves left less? map map! member? members more? node node? nodes parts right setchildren! setelt setleft! setright! setvalue! size? split value

count cyclic? elt empty empty? eq? every? insert! leaf? leaves left less? map map! member? members more? node node? nodes parts right setchildren! setelt setleft! setright! setvalue! size? value}

Abbreviation: | BTREE
Full name: | BinaryTree
Belongs to: | BinaryTreeCategory
Operations: | # = any? binaryTree children coerce copy count cyclic? elt empty empty? eq? every? leaf? leaves left less? map map! member? members more? node node? nodes parts right setchildren! setelt setleft! setright! setvalue! size? value

Abbreviation: | BITS
Full name: | Bits
Belongs to: | BitAggregate
Operations: | # < = \^{} and any? bits coerce concat construct convert copy copyInto! count delete elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first index? indices insert less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? nand new nor not or parts position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates reverse reverse! select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? swap! xor

Abbreviation: | BOOLEAN
Full name: | Boolean
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo Finite OrderedSet
Operations: | < = \^{} and coerce convert false implies index lookup max min nand nor not or random size true xor

Abbreviation: | CARD
Full name: | CardinalNumber
Belongs to: | CancellationAbelianMonoid Monoid OrderedSet RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = Aleph coerce countable? finite? generalizedContinuumHypothesisAssumed generalizedContinuumHypothesisAssumed? max min one? recip retract retractIfCan zero?

Abbreviation: | CARTEN
Full name: | CartesianTensor
Belongs to: | GradedAlgebra
Operations: | 0 1 * + - = coerce contract degree elt kroneckerDelta leviCivitaSymbol product rank ravel reindex retract retractIfCan transpose unravel

Abbreviation: | CCLASS
Full name: | CharacterClass
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo FiniteSetAggregate SetCategory
Operations: | # < = alphabetic alphanumeric any? bag brace cardinality charClass coerce complement construct convert copy count dictionary difference digit empty empty? eq? every? extract! find hexDigit index insert! inspect intersect less? lookup lowerCase map map! max member? members min more? parts random reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates select select! size size? subset? symmetricDifference union universe upperCase

Abbreviation: | CHAR
Full name: | Character
Belongs to: | OrderedFinite
Operations: | < = alphabetic? alphanumeric? char coerce digit? escape hexDigit? index lookup lowerCase lowerCase? max min ord quote random size space upperCase upperCase?

Abbreviation: | CLIF
Full name: | CliffordAlgebra
Belongs to: | Algebra Ring VectorSpace
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = characteristic coefficient coerce dimension e monomial one? recip zero?

Abbreviation: | COLOR
Full name: | Color
Belongs to: | AbelianSemiGroup
Operations: | * + = blue coerce color green hue numberOfHues red yellow

Abbreviation: | COMM
Full name: | Commutator
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce mkcomm

Abbreviation: | COMPLEX
Full name: | Complex
Belongs to: | ComplexCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch argument asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh basis characteristic characteristicPolynomial charthRoot coerce complex conditionP conjugate convert coordinates cos cosh cot coth createPrimitiveElement csc csch definingPolynomial derivationCoordinates differentiate discreteLog discriminant divide elt euclideanSize eval exp expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd gcdPolynomial generator imag imaginary index init inv lcm lift log lookup map max min minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm nthRoot one? order pi polarCoordinates prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random rank rational rational? rationalIfCan real recip reduce reducedSystem regularRepresentation rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan sec sech sin sinh size sizeLess? solveLinearPolynomialEquation sqrt squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial tableForDiscreteLogarithm tan tanh trace traceMatrix unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | CONTFRAC
Full name: | ContinuedFraction
Belongs to: | Algebra Field
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = approximants associates? characteristic coerce complete continuedFraction convergents denominators divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extend extendedEuclidean factor gcd inv lcm multiEuclidean numerators one? partialDenominators partialNumerators partialQuotients prime? principalIdeal quo recip reducedContinuedFraction reducedForm rem sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | DBASE
Full name: | Database
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | + - = coerce display elt fullDisplay

Abbreviation: | DFLOAT
Full name: | DoubleFloat
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo DifferentialRing FloatingPointSystem TranscendentalFunctionCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh base bits ceiling characteristic coerce convert cos cosh cot coth csc csch decreasePrecision differentiate digits divide euclideanSize exp exp1 exponent expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor float floor fractionPart gcd hash increasePrecision inv lcm log log10 log2 mantissa max min multiEuclidean negative? norm nthRoot one? order patternMatch pi positive? precision prime? principalIdeal quo rationalApproximation recip rem retract retractIfCan round sec sech sign sin sinh sizeLess? sqrt squareFree squareFreePart tan tanh truncate unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | DLIST
Full name: | DataList
Belongs to: | ListAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? children coerce concat concat! construct convert copy copyInto! count cycleEntry cycleLength cycleSplit! cycleTail cyclic? datalist delete delete! elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? explicitlyFinite? fill! find first index? indices insert insert! last leaf? leaves less? list map map! max maxIndex member? members merge merge! min minIndex more? new node? nodes parts position possiblyInfinite? qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates removeDuplicates! rest reverse reverse! second select select! setchildren! setelt setfirst! setlast! setrest! setvalue! size? sort sort! sorted? split! swap! tail third value

Abbreviation: | DECIMAL
Full name: | DecimalExpansion
Belongs to: | QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs associates? ceiling characteristic coerce convert decimal denom denominator differentiate divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor floor fractionPart gcd init inv lcm map max min multiEuclidean negative? nextItem numer numerator one? patternMatch positive? prime? principalIdeal quo random recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan sign sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | DHMATRIX
Full name: | DenavitHartenbergMatrix
Belongs to: | MatrixCategory
Operations: | # * ** + - / = antisymmetric? any? coerce column copy count determinant diagonal? diagonalMatrix elt empty empty? eq? every? exquo fill! horizConcat identity inverse less? listOfLists map map! matrix maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex minordet more? ncols new nrows nullSpace nullity parts qelt qsetelt! rank rotatex rotatey rotatez row rowEchelon scalarMatrix scale setColumn! setRow! setelt setsubMatrix! size? square? squareTop subMatrix swapColumns! swapRows! symmetric? translate transpose vertConcat zero

Abbreviation: | DEQUEUE
Full name: | Dequeue
Belongs to: | DequeueAggregate
Operations: | # = any? back bag bottom! coerce copy count depth dequeue dequeue! empty empty? enqueue! eq? every? extract! extractBottom! extractTop! front height insert! insertBottom! insertTop! inspect length less? map map! member? members more? parts pop! push! reverse! rotate! size? top top!

Abbreviation: | DERHAM
Full name: | DeRhamComplex
Belongs to: | LeftAlgebra RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = characteristic coefficient coerce degree exteriorDifferential generator homogeneous? leadingBasisTerm leadingCoefficient map one? recip reductum retract retractIfCan retractable? totalDifferential zero?

Abbreviation: | DSMP
Full name: | DifferentialSparseMultivariatePolynomial
Belongs to: | DifferentialPolynomialCategory RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP content convert degree differentialVariables differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? initial isExpt isPlus isTimes isobaric? lcm leader leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable makeVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? order patternMatch prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum resultant retract retractIfCan separant solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables weight weights zero?

Abbreviation: | DPMM
Full name: | DirectProductMatrixModule
Belongs to: | DirectProductCategory LeftModule
Operations: | 0 1 # * ** + - / < = D abs any? characteristic coerce copy count differentiate dimension directProduct dot elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! first index index? indices less? lookup map map! max maxIndex member? members min minIndex more? negative? one? parts positive? qelt qsetelt! random recip reducedSystem retract retractIfCan setelt sign size size? sup swap! unitVector zero?

Abbreviation: | DPMO
Full name: | DirectProductModule
Belongs to: | DirectProductCategory LeftModule
Operations: | 0 1 # * ** + - / < = D abs any? characteristic coerce copy count differentiate dimension directProduct dot elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! first index index? indices less? lookup map map! max maxIndex member? members min minIndex more? negative? one? parts positive? qelt qsetelt! random recip reducedSystem retract retractIfCan setelt sign size size? sup swap! unitVector zero?

Abbreviation: | DIRPROD
Full name: | DirectProduct
Belongs to: | DirectProductCategory
Operations: | 0 1 # * ** + - / < = D abs any? characteristic coerce copy count differentiate dimension directProduct dot elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! first index index? indices less? lookup map map! max maxIndex member? members min minIndex more? negative? one? parts positive? qelt qsetelt! random recip reducedSystem retract retractIfCan setelt sign size size? sup swap! unitVector zero?

Abbreviation: | DMP
Full name: | DistributedMultivariatePolynomial
Belongs to: | PolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP const content convert degree differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum reorder resultant retract retractIfCan solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables zero?

Abbreviation: | DROPT
Full name: | DrawOption
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = adaptive clip coerce colorFunction coordinate coordinates curveColor option option? pointColor range ranges space style title toScale tubePoints tubeRadius unit var1Steps var2Steps

Abbreviation: | EFULS
Full name: | ElementaryFunctionsUnivariateLaurentSeries
Belongs to: | PartialTranscendentalFunctions
Operations: | ** acos acosIfCan acosh acoshIfCan acot acotIfCan acoth acothIfCan acsc acscIfCan acsch acschIfCan asec asecIfCan asech asechIfCan asin asinIfCan asinh asinhIfCan atan atanIfCan atanh atanhIfCan cos cosIfCan cosh coshIfCan cot cotIfCan coth cothIfCan csc cscIfCan csch cschIfCan exp expIfCan log logIfCan nthRootIfCan sec secIfCan sech sechIfCan sin sinIfCan sinh sinhIfCan tan tanIfCan tanh tanhIfCan

Abbreviation: | EFUPXS
Full name: | ElementaryFunctionsUnivariatePuiseuxSeries
Belongs to: | PartialTranscendentalFunctions
Operations: | ** acos acosIfCan acosh acoshIfCan acot acotIfCan acoth acothIfCan acsc acscIfCan acsch acschIfCan asec asecIfCan asech asechIfCan asin asinIfCan asinh asinhIfCan atan atanIfCan atanh atanhIfCan cos cosIfCan cosh coshIfCan cot cotIfCan coth cothIfCan csc cscIfCan csch cschIfCan exp expIfCan log logIfCan nthRootIfCan sec secIfCan sech sechIfCan sin sinIfCan sinh sinhIfCan tan tanIfCan tanh tanhIfCan

Abbreviation: | EQTBL
Full name: | EqTable
Belongs to: | TableAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce construct copy count dictionary elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert! inspect key? keys less? map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? parts qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates search select select! setelt size? swap! table

Abbreviation: | EQ
Full name: | Equation
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo InnerEvalable Object SetCategory
Operations: | * ** + - = coerce equation eval lhs map rhs

Abbreviation: | EMR
Full name: | EuclideanModularRing
Belongs to: | EuclideanDomain
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = associates? characteristic coerce divide euclideanSize exQuo expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean gcd inv lcm modulus multiEuclidean one? principalIdeal quo recip reduce rem sizeLess? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | EXIT
Full name: | Exit
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce

Abbreviation: | EXPR
Full name: | Expression
Belongs to: | AlgebraicallyClosedFunctionSpace CombinatorialOpsCategory FunctionSpace LiouvillianFunctionCategory RetractableTo SpecialFunctionCategory TranscendentalFunctionCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = Beta Ci D Ei Gamma Si abs acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch airyAi airyBi applyQuote asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh belong? besselI besselJ besselK besselY binomial box characteristic charthRoot coerce commutator conjugate convert cos cosh cot coth csc csch definingPolynomial denom denominator differentiate digamma dilog distribute divide elt erf euclideanSize eval exp expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorial factorials freeOf? gcd ground ground? height integral inv is? isExpt isMult isPlus isPower isTimes kernel kernels lcm li log mainKernel map max min minPoly multiEuclidean nthRoot numer numerator one? operator operators paren patternMatch permutation pi polygamma prime? principalIdeal product quo recip reduce reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan rootOf rootsOf sec sech sin sinh sizeLess? sqrt squareFree squareFreePart subst summation tan tanh tower unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables zero? zeroOf zerosOf

Abbreviation: | EAB
Full name: | ExtAlgBasis
Belongs to: | OrderedSet
Operations: | < = Nul coerce degree exponents max min

Abbreviation: | FR
Full name: | Factored
Belongs to: | Algebra DifferentialExtension Eltable Evalable FullyEvalableOver FullyRetractableTo GcdDomain InnerEvalable IntegralDomain RealConstant UniqueFactorizationDomain
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = D associates? characteristic coerce convert differentiate elt eval expand exponent exquo factor factorList factors flagFactor gcd irreducibleFactor lcm makeFR map nilFactor nthExponent nthFactor nthFlag numberOfFactors one? prime? primeFactor rational rational? rationalIfCan recip retract retractIfCan sqfrFactor squareFree squareFreePart unit unit? unitCanonical unitNormal unitNormalize zero?

Abbreviation: | FNAME
Full name: | FileName
Belongs to: | FileNameCategory
Operations: | = coerce directory exists? extension filename name new readable? writable?

Abbreviation: | FILE
Full name: | File
Belongs to: | FileCategory
Operations: | = close! coerce iomode name open read! readIfCan! reopen! write!

Abbreviation: | FDIV
Full name: | FiniteDivisor
Belongs to: | AbelianGroup
Operations: | 0 * + - = algsplit coerce divisor finiteBasis generator ideal lSpaceBasis mkBasicDiv principal? reduce zero?

Abbreviation: | FFCGP
Full name: | FiniteFieldCyclicGroupExtensionByPolynomial
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator getZechTable inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FFCGX
Full name: | FiniteFieldCyclicGroupExtension
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator getZechTable inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FFCG
Full name: | FiniteFieldCyclicGroup
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator getZechTable inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FFP
Full name: | FiniteFieldExtensionByPolynomial
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FFX
Full name: | FiniteFieldExtension
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FFNBP
Full name: | FiniteFieldNormalBasisExtensionByPolynomial
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator getMultiplicationMatrix getMultiplicationTable inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? sizeMultiplication squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FFNBX
Full name: | FiniteFieldNormalBasisExtension
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator getMultiplicationMatrix getMultiplicationTable inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? sizeMultiplication squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FFNB
Full name: | FiniteFieldNormalBasis
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator getMultiplicationMatrix getMultiplicationTable inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? sizeMultiplication squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FF
Full name: | FiniteField
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | FARRAY
Full name: | FlexibleArray
Belongs to: | ExtensibleLinearAggregate OneDimensionalArrayAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? coerce concat concat! construct convert copy copyInto! count delete delete! elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first flexibleArray index? indices insert insert! less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge merge! min minIndex more? new parts physicalLength physicalLength! position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates removeDuplicates! reverse reverse! select select! setelt shrinkable size? sort sort! sorted? swap!

Abbreviation: | FLOAT
Full name: | Float
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo ConvertibleTo DifferentialRing FloatingPointSystem TranscendentalFunctionCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh base bits ceiling characteristic coerce convert cos cosh cot coth csc csch decreasePrecision differentiate digits divide euclideanSize exp exp1 exponent expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor float floor fractionPart gcd increasePrecision inv lcm log log10 log2 mantissa max min multiEuclidean negative? norm normalize nthRoot one? order outputFixed outputFloating outputGeneral outputSpacing patternMatch pi positive? precision prime? principalIdeal quo rationalApproximation recip relerror rem retract retractIfCan round sec sech shift sign sin sinh sizeLess? sqrt squareFree squareFreePart tan tanh truncate unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | FRIDEAL
Full name: | FractionalIdeal
Belongs to: | Group
Operations: | 1 * ** / = basis coerce commutator conjugate denom ideal inv minimize norm numer one? randomLC recip

Abbreviation: | FRAC
Full name: | Fraction
Belongs to: | QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs associates? ceiling characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP convert denom denominator differentiate divide elt euclideanSize eval expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial floor fractionPart gcd gcdPolynomial init inv lcm map max min multiEuclidean negative? nextItem numer numerator one? patternMatch positive? prime? principalIdeal quo random recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan sign sizeLess? solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | FRMOD
Full name: | FramedModule
Belongs to: | Monoid
Operations: | 1 * ** = basis coerce module norm one? recip

Abbreviation: | FAGROUP
Full name: | FreeAbelianGroup
Belongs to: | AbelianGroup FreeAbelianMonoidCategory Module OrderedSet
Operations: | 0 * + - < = coefficient coerce highCommonTerms mapCoef mapGen max min nthCoef nthFactor retract retractIfCan size terms zero?

Abbreviation: | FAMONOID
Full name: | FreeAbelianMonoid
Belongs to: | FreeAbelianMonoidCategory
Operations: | 0 * + - = coefficient coerce highCommonTerms mapCoef mapGen nthCoef nthFactor retract retractIfCan size terms zero?

Abbreviation: | FGROUP
Full name: | FreeGroup
Belongs to: | Group RetractableTo
Operations: | 1 * ** / = coerce commutator conjugate factors inv mapExpon mapGen nthExpon nthFactor one? recip retract retractIfCan size

Abbreviation: | FM
Full name: | FreeModule
Belongs to: | BiModule IndexedDirectProductCategory Module
Operations: | 0 * + - = coerce leadingCoefficient leadingSupport map monomial reductum zero?

Abbreviation: | FMONOID
Full name: | FreeMonoid
Belongs to: | Monoid OrderedSet RetractableTo
Operations: | 1 * ** < = coerce divide factors hclf hcrf lquo mapExpon mapGen max min nthExpon nthFactor one? overlap recip retract retractIfCan rquo size

Abbreviation: | FNLA
Full name: | FreeNilpotentLie
Belongs to: | NonAssociativeAlgebra
Operations: | 0 * ** + - = antiCommutator associator coerce commutator deepExpand dimension generator leftPower rightPower shallowExpand zero?

Abbreviation: | FUNCTION
Full name: | FunctionCalled
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce name

Abbreviation: | GDMP
Full name: | GeneralDistributedMultivariatePolynomial
Belongs to: | PolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP const content convert degree differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum reorder resultant retract retractIfCan solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables zero?

Abbreviation: | GSTBL
Full name: | GeneralSparseTable
Belongs to: | TableAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce construct copy count dictionary elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert! inspect key? keys less? map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? parts qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates search select select! setelt size? swap! table

Abbreviation: | GCNAALG
Full name: | GenericNonAssociativeAlgebra
Belongs to: | FramedNonAssociativeAlgebra LeftModule
Operations: | 0 * ** + - = JacobiIdentity? JordanAlgebra? alternative? antiAssociative? antiCommutative? antiCommutator apply associative? associator associatorDependence basis coerce commutative? commutator conditionsForIdempotents convert coordinates elt flexible? generic genericLeftDiscriminant genericLeftMinimalPolynomial genericLeftNorm genericLeftTrace genericLeftTraceForm genericRightDiscriminant genericRightMinimalPolynomial genericRightNorm genericRightTrace genericRightTraceForm jordanAdmissible? leftAlternative? leftCharacteristicPolynomial leftDiscriminant leftMinimalPolynomial leftNorm leftPower leftRankPolynomial leftRecip leftRegularRepresentation leftTrace leftTraceMatrix leftUnit leftUnits lieAdmissible? lieAlgebra? noncommutativeJordanAlgebra? plenaryPower powerAssociative? rank recip represents rightAlternative? rightCharacteristicPolynomial rightDiscriminant rightMinimalPolynomial rightNorm rightPower rightRankPolynomial rightRecip rightRegularRepresentation rightTrace rightTraceMatrix rightUnit rightUnits someBasis structuralConstants unit zero?

Abbreviation: | GRIMAGE
Full name: | GraphImage
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = appendPoint coerce component graphImage key makeGraphImage point pointLists putColorInfo ranges units

Abbreviation: | HASHTBL
Full name: | HashTable
Belongs to: | TableAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce construct copy count dictionary elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert! inspect key? keys less? map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? parts qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates search select select! setelt size? swap! table

Abbreviation: | HEAP
Full name: | Heap
Belongs to: | PriorityQueueAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce copy count empty empty? eq? every? extract! heap insert! inspect less? map map! max member? members merge merge! more? parts size?

Abbreviation: | HEXADEC
Full name: | HexadecimalExpansion
Belongs to: | QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs associates? ceiling characteristic coerce convert denom denominator differentiate divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor floor fractionPart gcd hex init inv lcm map max min multiEuclidean negative? nextItem numer numerator one? patternMatch positive? prime? principalIdeal quo random recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan sign sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | ICARD
Full name: | IndexCard
Belongs to: | OrderedSet
Operations: | < = coerce display elt fullDisplay max min

Abbreviation: | IBITS
Full name: | IndexedBits
Belongs to: | BitAggregate
Operations: | # < = And Not Or \^{} and any? coerce concat construct convert copy copyInto! count delete elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first index? indices insert less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? nand new nor not or parts position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates reverse reverse! select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? swap! xor

Abbreviation: | IDPAG
Full name: | IndexedDirectProductAbelianGroup
Belongs to: | AbelianGroup IndexedDirectProductCategory
Operations: | 0 * + - = coerce leadingCoefficient leadingSupport map monomial reductum zero?

Abbreviation: | IDPAM
Full name: | IndexedDirectProductAbelianMonoid
Belongs to: | AbelianMonoid IndexedDirectProductCategory
Operations: | 0 * + = coerce leadingCoefficient leadingSupport map monomial reductum zero?

Abbreviation: | IDPO
Full name: | IndexedDirectProductObject
Belongs to: | IndexedDirectProductCategory
Operations: | = coerce leadingCoefficient leadingSupport map monomial reductum

Abbreviation: | IDPOAMS
Full name: | IndexedDirectProductOrderedAbelianMonoidSup
Belongs to: | IndexedDirectProductCategory OrderedAbelianMonoidSup
Operations: | 0 * + - < = coerce leadingCoefficient leadingSupport map max min monomial reductum sup zero?

Abbreviation: | IDPOAM
Full name: | IndexedDirectProductOrderedAbelianMonoid
Belongs to: | IndexedDirectProductCategory OrderedAbelianMonoid
Operations: | 0 * + < = coerce leadingCoefficient leadingSupport map max min monomial reductum zero?

Abbreviation: | INDE
Full name: | IndexedExponents
Belongs to: | IndexedDirectProductCategory OrderedAbelianMonoidSup
Operations: | 0 * + - < = coerce leadingCoefficient leadingSupport map max min monomial reductum sup zero?

Abbreviation: | IFARRAY
Full name: | IndexedFlexibleArray
Belongs to: | ExtensibleLinearAggregate OneDimensionalArrayAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? coerce concat concat! construct convert copy copyInto! count delete delete! elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first flexibleArray index? indices insert insert! less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge merge! min minIndex more? new parts physicalLength physicalLength! position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates removeDuplicates! reverse reverse! select select! setelt shrinkable size? sort sort! sorted? swap!

Abbreviation: | ILIST
Full name: | IndexedList
Belongs to: | ListAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? child? children coerce concat concat! construct convert copy copyInto! count cycleEntry cycleLength cycleSplit! cycleTail cyclic? delete delete! distance elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? explicitlyFinite? fill! find first index? indices insert insert! last leaf? less? list map map! max maxIndex member? members merge merge! min minIndex more? new node? nodes parts position possiblyInfinite? qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates removeDuplicates! rest reverse reverse! second select select! setchildren! setelt setfirst! setlast! setrest! setvalue! size? sort sort! sorted? split! swap! tail third value

Abbreviation: | IMATRIX
Full name: | IndexedMatrix
Belongs to: | MatrixCategory
Operations: | # * ** + - / = antisymmetric? any? coerce column copy count determinant diagonal? diagonalMatrix elt empty empty? eq? every? exquo fill! horizConcat inverse less? listOfLists map map! matrix maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex minordet more? ncols new nrows nullSpace nullity parts qelt qsetelt! rank row rowEchelon scalarMatrix setColumn! setRow! setelt setsubMatrix! size? square? squareTop subMatrix swapColumns! swapRows! symmetric? transpose vertConcat zero

Abbreviation: | IARRAY1
Full name: | IndexedOneDimensionalArray
Belongs to: | OneDimensionalArrayAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? coerce concat construct convert copy copyInto! count delete elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first index? indices insert less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? new parts position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates reverse reverse! select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? swap!

Abbreviation: | ISTRING
Full name: | IndexedString
Belongs to: | StringAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? coerce concat construct copy copyInto! count delete elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first hash index? indices insert leftTrim less? lowerCase lowerCase! map map! match? max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? new parts position prefix? qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates replace reverse reverse! rightTrim select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? split substring? suffix? swap! trim upperCase upperCase!

Abbreviation: | IARRAY2
Full name: | IndexedTwoDimensionalArray
Belongs to: | TwoDimensionalArrayCategory
Operations: | # = any? coerce column copy count elt empty empty? eq? every? fill! less? map map! maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex more? ncols new nrows parts qelt qsetelt! row setColumn! setRow! setelt size?

Abbreviation: | IVECTOR
Full name: | IndexedVector
Belongs to: | VectorCategory
Operations: | # * + - < = any? coerce concat construct convert copy copyInto! count delete dot elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first index? indices insert less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? new parts position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates reverse reverse! select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? swap! zero

Abbreviation: | ITUPLE
Full name: | InfiniteTuple
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo
Operations: | coerce construct filterUntil filterWhile generate map select

Abbreviation: | IFF
Full name: | InnerFiniteField
Belongs to: | FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | IFAMON
Full name: | InnerFreeAbelianMonoid
Belongs to: | FreeAbelianMonoidCategory
Operations: | 0 * + - = coefficient coerce highCommonTerms mapCoef mapGen nthCoef nthFactor retract retractIfCan size terms zero?

Abbreviation: | IIARRAY2
Full name: | InnerIndexedTwoDimensionalArray
Belongs to: | TwoDimensionalArrayCategory
Operations: | # = any? coerce column copy count elt empty empty? eq? every? fill! less? map map! maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex more? ncols new nrows parts qelt qsetelt! row setColumn! setRow! setelt size?

Abbreviation: | IPADIC
Full name: | InnerPAdicInteger
Belongs to: | PAdicIntegerCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = approximate associates? characteristic coerce complete digits divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extend extendedEuclidean gcd lcm moduloP modulus multiEuclidean one? order principalIdeal quo quotientByP recip rem sizeLess? sqrt unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | IPF
Full name: | InnerPrimeField
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField FiniteFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP convert coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | ITAYLOR
Full name: | InnerTaylorSeries
Belongs to: | IntegralDomain Ring
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = associates? characteristic coefficients coerce exquo one? order pole? recip series unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | INFORM
Full name: | InputForm
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo SExpressionCategory
Operations: | 0 1 # * ** + / = atom? binary car cdr coerce compile convert declare destruct elt eq expr flatten float float? function integer integer? interpret lambda list? null? pair? string string? symbol symbol? uequal unparse

Abbreviation: | ZMOD
Full name: | IntegerMod
Belongs to: | CommutativeRing ConvertibleTo Finite StepThrough
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = characteristic coerce convert index init lookup nextItem one? random recip size zero?

Abbreviation: | INT
Full name: | Integer
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo IntegerNumberSystem
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = D abs addmod associates? base binomial bit? characteristic coerce convert copy dec differentiate divide euclideanSize even? expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorial gcd hash inc init invmod lcm length mask max min mulmod multiEuclidean negative? nextItem odd? one? patternMatch permutation positive? positiveRemainder powmod prime? principalIdeal quo random rational rational? rationalIfCan recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan shift sign sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart submod symmetricRemainder unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | IR
Full name: | IntegrationResult
Belongs to: | Module RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 * + - = D coerce differentiate elem? integral logpart mkAnswer notelem ratpart retract retractIfCan zero?

Abbreviation: | KERNEL
Full name: | Kernel
Belongs to: | CachableSet ConvertibleTo Patternable
Operations: | < = argument coerce convert height is? kernel max min name operator position setPosition symbolIfCan

Abbreviation: | KAFILE
Full name: | KeyedAccessFile
Belongs to: | FileCategory TableAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag close! coerce construct copy count dictionary elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert! inspect iomode key? keys less? map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? name open pack! parts qelt qsetelt! read! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates reopen! search select select! setelt size? swap! table write!

Abbreviation: | LAUPOL
Full name: | LaurentPolynomial
Belongs to: | CharacteristicNonZero CharacteristicZero ConvertibleTo DifferentialExtension EuclideanDomain FullyRetractableTo IntegralDomain RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coerce convert degree differentiate divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean gcd lcm leadingCoefficient monomial monomial? multiEuclidean one? order principalIdeal quo recip reductum rem retract retractIfCan separate sizeLess? trailingCoefficient unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | LIB
Full name: | Library
Belongs to: | TableAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce construct copy count dictionary elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert! inspect key? keys less? library map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? pack! parts qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates search select select! setelt size? swap! table

Abbreviation: | LSQM
Full name: | LieSquareMatrix
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo FramedNonAssociativeAlgebra SquareMatrixCategory
Operations: | 0 1 # * ** + - / = D JacobiIdentity? JordanAlgebra? alternative? antiAssociative? antiCommutative? antiCommutator antisymmetric? any? apply associative? associator associatorDependence basis characteristic coerce column commutative? commutator conditionsForIdempotents convert coordinates copy count determinant diagonal diagonal? diagonalMatrix diagonalProduct differentiate elt empty empty? eq? every? exquo flexible? inverse jordanAdmissible? leftAlternative? leftCharacteristicPolynomial leftDiscriminant leftMinimalPolynomial leftNorm leftPower leftRankPolynomial leftRecip leftRegularRepresentation leftTrace leftTraceMatrix leftUnit leftUnits less? lieAdmissible? lieAlgebra? listOfLists map map! matrix maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex minordet more? ncols noncommutativeJordanAlgebra? nrows nullSpace nullity one? parts plenaryPower powerAssociative? qelt rank recip reducedSystem represents retract retractIfCan rightAlternative? rightCharacteristicPolynomial rightDiscriminant rightMinimalPolynomial rightNorm rightPower rightRankPolynomial rightRecip rightRegularRepresentation rightTrace rightTraceMatrix rightUnit rightUnits row rowEchelon scalarMatrix size? someBasis square? structuralConstants symmetric? trace unit zero?

Abbreviation: | LODO
Full name: | LinearOrdinaryDifferentialOperator
Belongs to: | MonogenicLinearOperator
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = D characteristic coefficient coerce degree elt leadingCoefficient leftDivide leftExactQuotient leftGcd leftLcm leftQuotient leftRemainder minimumDegree monomial one? recip reductum rightDivide rightExactQuotient rightGcd rightLcm rightQuotient rightRemainder zero?

Abbreviation: | LMOPS
Full name: | ListMonoidOps
Belongs to: | RetractableTo SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce leftMult listOfMonoms makeMulti makeTerm makeUnit mapExpon mapGen nthExpon nthFactor outputForm plus retract retractIfCan reverse reverse! rightMult size

Abbreviation: | LMDICT
Full name: | ListMultiDictionary
Belongs to: | MultiDictionary
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce construct convert copy count dictionary duplicates duplicates? empty empty? eq? every? extract! find insert! inspect less? map map! member? members more? parts reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates removeDuplicates! select select! size? substitute

Abbreviation: | LIST
Full name: | List
Belongs to: | ListAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? append child? children coerce concat concat! cons construct convert copy copyInto! count cycleEntry cycleLength cycleSplit! cycleTail cyclic? delete delete! distance elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? explicitlyFinite? fill! find first index? indices insert insert! last leaf? less? list map map! max maxIndex member? members merge merge! min minIndex more? new nil node? nodes null parts position possiblyInfinite? qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates removeDuplicates! rest reverse reverse! second select select! setDifference setIntersection setUnion setchildren! setelt setfirst! setlast! setrest! setvalue! size? sort sort! sorted? split! swap! tail third value

Abbreviation: | LA
Full name: | LocalAlgebra
Belongs to: | Algebra OrderedRing
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = abs characteristic coerce denom max min negative? numer one? positive? recip sign zero?

Abbreviation: | LO
Full name: | Localize
Belongs to: | Module OrderedAbelianGroup
Operations: | 0 * + - / < = coerce denom max min numer zero?

Abbreviation: | MKCHSET
Full name: | MakeCachableSet
Belongs to: | CachableSet CoercibleTo
Operations: | < = coerce max min position setPosition

Abbreviation: | MKODRING
Full name: | MakeOrdinaryDifferentialRing
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo DifferentialRing
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = D characteristic coerce differentiate one? recip zero?

Abbreviation: | MATRIX
Full name: | Matrix
Belongs to: | MatrixCategory
Operations: | # * ** + - / = antisymmetric? any? coerce column copy count determinant diagonal? diagonalMatrix elt empty empty? eq? every? exquo fill! horizConcat inverse less? listOfLists map map! matrix maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex minordet more? ncols new nrows nullSpace nullity parts qelt qsetelt! rank row rowEchelon scalarMatrix setColumn! setRow! setelt setsubMatrix! size? square? squareTop subMatrix swapColumns! swapRows! symmetric? transpose vertConcat zero

Abbreviation: | MODMON
Full name: | ModMonic
Belongs to: | Finite UnivariatePolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = An D UnVectorise Vectorise associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce composite computePowers conditionP content degree differentiate discriminant divide divideExponents elt euclideanSize eval expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? index init integrate isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial lift lookup mainVariable makeSUP map mapExponents max min minimumDegree modulus monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multiEuclidean multiplyExponents multivariate nextItem numberOfMonomials one? order pow prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart principalIdeal pseudoDivide pseudoQuotient pseudoRemainder quo random recip reduce reducedSystem reductum rem resultant retract retractIfCan separate setPoly size sizeLess? solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial subResultantGcd totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate unmakeSUP variables vectorise zero?

Abbreviation: | MODFIELD
Full name: | ModularField
Belongs to: | Field
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = associates? characteristic coerce divide euclideanSize exQuo expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor gcd inv lcm modulus multiEuclidean one? prime? principalIdeal quo recip reduce rem sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | MODRING
Full name: | ModularRing
Belongs to: | Ring
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = characteristic coerce exQuo inv modulus one? recip reduce zero?

Abbreviation: | MOEBIUS
Full name: | MoebiusTransform
Belongs to: | Group
Operations: | 1 * ** / = coerce commutator conjugate eval inv moebius one? recip scale shift

Abbreviation: | MRING
Full name: | MonoidRing
Belongs to: | Algebra CharacteristicNonZero CharacteristicZero Finite RetractableTo Ring
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce index leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial lookup map monomial monomial? monomials numberOfMonomials one? random recip reductum retract retractIfCan size terms zero?

Abbreviation: | MSET
Full name: | Multiset
Belongs to: | MultiSetAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? bag brace coerce construct convert copy count dictionary difference duplicates empty empty? eq? every? extract! find insert! inspect intersect less? map map! member? members more? multiset parts reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates removeDuplicates! select select! size? subset? symmetricDifference union

Abbreviation: | MPOLY
Full name: | MultivariatePolynomial
Belongs to: | PolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP content convert degree differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum resultant retract retractIfCan solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables zero?

Abbreviation: | NDP
Full name: | NewDirectProduct
Belongs to: | DirectProductCategory
Operations: | 0 1 # * ** + - / < = D abs any? characteristic coerce copy count differentiate dimension directProduct dot elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! first index index? indices less? lookup map map! max maxIndex member? members min minIndex more? negative? one? parts positive? qelt qsetelt! random recip reducedSystem retract retractIfCan setelt sign size size? sup swap! unitVector zero?

Abbreviation: | NDMP
Full name: | NewDistributedMultivariatePolynomial
Belongs to: | PolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP const content convert degree differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum reorder resultant retract retractIfCan solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables zero?

Abbreviation: | NONE
Full name: | None
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce

Abbreviation: | NNI
Full name: | NonNegativeInteger
Belongs to: | Monoid OrderedAbelianMonoidSup
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = coerce divide exquo gcd max min one? quo recip rem sup zero?

Abbreviation: | OCT
Full name: | Octonion
Belongs to: | FullyRetractableTo OctonionCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = abs characteristic charthRoot coerce conjugate convert elt eval imagE imagI imagJ imagK imagi imagj imagk index inv lookup map max min norm octon one? random rational rational? rationalIfCan real recip retract retractIfCan size zero?

Abbreviation: | ARRAY1
Full name: | OneDimensionalArray
Belongs to: | OneDimensionalArrayAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? coerce concat construct convert copy copyInto! count delete elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first index? indices insert less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? new oneDimensionalArray parts position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates reverse reverse! select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? swap!

Abbreviation: | ONECOMP
Full name: | OnePointCompletion
Belongs to: | AbelianGroup FullyRetractableTo OrderedRing SetCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = abs characteristic coerce finite? infinite? infinity max min negative? one? positive? rational rational? rationalIfCan recip retract retractIfCan sign zero?

Abbreviation: | OP
Full name: | Operator
Belongs to: | Algebra CharacteristicNonZero CharacteristicZero Eltable RetractableTo Ring
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = characteristic charthRoot coerce elt evaluate one? opeval recip retract retractIfCan zero?

Abbreviation: | OMLO
Full name: | OppositeMonogenicLinearOperator
Belongs to: | DifferentialRing MonogenicLinearOperator
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = D characteristic coefficient coerce degree differentiate leadingCoefficient minimumDegree monomial one? op po recip reductum zero?

Abbreviation: | ORDCOMP
Full name: | OrderedCompletion
Belongs to: | AbelianGroup FullyRetractableTo OrderedRing SetCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = abs characteristic coerce finite? infinite? max min minusInfinity negative? one? plusInfinity positive? rational rational? rationalIfCan recip retract retractIfCan sign whatInfinity zero?

Abbreviation: | ODP
Full name: | OrderedDirectProduct
Belongs to: | DirectProductCategory
Operations: | 0 1 # * ** + - / < = D abs any? characteristic coerce copy count differentiate dimension directProduct dot elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! first index index? indices less? lookup map map! max maxIndex member? members min minIndex more? negative? one? parts positive? qelt qsetelt! random recip reducedSystem retract retractIfCan setelt sign size size? sup swap! unitVector zero?

Abbreviation: | OVAR
Full name: | OrderedVariableList
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo OrderedFinite
Operations: | < = coerce convert index lookup max min random size variable

Abbreviation: | ODPOL
Full name: | OrderlyDifferentialPolynomial
Belongs to: | DifferentialPolynomialCategory RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP content degree differentialVariables differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? initial isExpt isPlus isTimes isobaric? lcm leader leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable makeVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? order prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum resultant retract retractIfCan separant solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables weight weights zero?

Abbreviation: | ODVAR
Full name: | OrderlyDifferentialVariable
Belongs to: | DifferentialVariableCategory
Operations: | < = D coerce differentiate makeVariable max min order retract retractIfCan variable weight

Abbreviation: | ODR
Full name: | OrdinaryDifferentialRing
Belongs to: | Algebra DifferentialRing Field
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D associates? characteristic coerce differentiate divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor gcd inv lcm multiEuclidean one? prime? principalIdeal quo recip rem sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | OSI
Full name: | OrdSetInts
Belongs to: | OrderedSet
Operations: | < = coerce max min value

Abbreviation: | OUTFORM
Full name: | OutputForm
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | * ** + - / < <= = > >= D SEGMENT \^{}= and assign blankSeparate box brace bracket center coerce commaSeparate differentiate div dot elt empty exquo hconcat height hspace infix infix? int label left matrix message messagePrint not or outputForm over overbar paren pile postfix prefix presub presuper prime print prod quo quote rarrow rem right root rspace scripts semicolonSeparate slash string sub subHeight sum super superHeight supersub vconcat vspace width zag

Abbreviation: | PADIC
Full name: | PAdicInteger
Belongs to: | PAdicIntegerCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - = approximate associates? characteristic coerce complete digits divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extend extendedEuclidean gcd lcm moduloP modulus multiEuclidean one? order principalIdeal quo quotientByP recip rem sizeLess? sqrt unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | PADICRC
Full name: | PAdicRationalConstructor
Belongs to: | QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs approximate associates? ceiling characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP continuedFraction convert denom denominator differentiate divide elt euclideanSize eval expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial floor fractionPart gcd gcdPolynomial init inv lcm map max min multiEuclidean negative? nextItem numer numerator one? patternMatch positive? prime? principalIdeal quo random recip reducedSystem rem removeZeroes retract retractIfCan sign sizeLess? solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | PADICRAT
Full name: | PAdicRational
Belongs to: | QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D approximate associates? characteristic coerce continuedFraction denom denominator differentiate divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor fractionPart gcd inv lcm map multiEuclidean numer numerator one? prime? principalIdeal quo recip reducedSystem rem removeZeroes retract retractIfCan sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | PALETTE
Full name: | Palette
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = bright coerce dark dim hue light pastel shade

Abbreviation: | PARPCURV
Full name: | ParametricPlaneCurve
Belongs to: |
Operations: | coordinate curve

Abbreviation: | PARSCURV
Full name: | ParametricSpaceCurve
Belongs to: |
Operations: | coordinate curve

Abbreviation: | PARSURF
Full name: | ParametricSurface
Belongs to: |
Operations: | coordinate surface

Abbreviation: | PFR
Full name: | PartialFraction
Belongs to: | Algebra Field
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = associates? characteristic coerce compactFraction divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor firstDenom firstNumer gcd inv lcm multiEuclidean nthFractionalTerm numberOfFractionalTerms one? padicFraction padicallyExpand partialFraction prime? principalIdeal quo recip rem sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | PRTITION
Full name: | Partition
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo OrderedCancellationAbelianMonoid
Operations: | 0 * + - < = coerce conjugate convert max min partition pdct powers zero?

Abbreviation: | PATLRES
Full name: | PatternMatchListResult
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = atoms coerce failed failed? lists makeResult new

Abbreviation: | PATRES
Full name: | PatternMatchResult
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = addMatch addMatchRestricted coerce construct destruct failed failed? getMatch insertMatch new satisfy? union

Abbreviation: | PATTERN
Full name: | Pattern
Belongs to: | RetractableTo SetCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + / = addBadValue coerce constant? convert copy depth elt generic? getBadValues hasPredicate? hasTopPredicate? inR? isExpt isList isOp isPlus isPower isQuotient isTimes multiple? optional? optpair patternVariable predicates quoted? resetBadValues retract retractIfCan setPredicates setTopPredicate symbol? topPredicate variables withPredicates

Abbreviation: | PENDTREE
Full name: | PendantTree
Belongs to: | BinaryRecursiveAggregate
Operations: | # = any? children coerce copy count cyclic? elt empty empty? eq? every? leaf? leaves left less? map map! member? members more? node? nodes parts ptree right setchildren! setelt setleft! setright! setvalue! size? value

Abbreviation: | PERMGRP
Full name: | PermutationGroup
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | < <= = base coerce degree elt generators initializeGroupForWordProblem member? movedPoints orbit orbits order permutationGroup random strongGenerators wordInGenerators wordInStrongGenerators wordsForStrongGenerators

Abbreviation: | PERM
Full name: | Permutation
Belongs to: | PermutationCategory
Operations: | 1 * ** / < = coerce coerceImages coerceListOfPairs coercePreimagesImages commutator conjugate cycle cyclePartition cycles degree elt eval even? fixedPoints inv listRepresentation max min movedPoints numberOfCycles odd? one? orbit order recip sign sort

Abbreviation: | HACKPI
Full name: | Pi
Belongs to: | CharacteristicZero CoercibleTo ConvertibleTo Field RealConstant RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = associates? characteristic coerce convert divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor gcd inv lcm multiEuclidean one? pi prime? principalIdeal quo recip rem retract retractIfCan sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | ACPLOT
Full name: | PlaneAlgebraicCurvePlot
Belongs to: | PlottablePlaneCurveCategory
Operations: | coerce listBranches makeSketch refine xRange yRange

Abbreviation: | PLOT3D
Full name: | Plot3D
Belongs to: | PlottableSpaceCurveCategory
Operations: | adaptive3D? coerce debug3D listBranches maxPoints3D minPoints3D numFunEvals3D plot pointPlot refine screenResolution3D setAdaptive3D setMaxPoints3D setMinPoints3D setScreenResolution3D tRange tValues xRange yRange zRange zoom

Abbreviation: | PLOT
Full name: | Plot
Belongs to: | PlottablePlaneCurveCategory
Operations: | adaptive? coerce debug listBranches maxPoints minPoints numFunEvals parametric? plot plotPolar pointPlot refine screenResolution setAdaptive setMaxPoints setMinPoints setScreenResolution tRange xRange yRange zoom

Abbreviation: | POINT
Full name: | Point
Belongs to: | PointCategory
Operations: | # * + - < = any? coerce concat construct convert copy copyInto! count cross delete dimension dot elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extend fill! find first index? indices insert length less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? new parts point position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates reverse reverse! select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? swap! zero

Abbreviation: | IDEAL
Full name: | PolynomialIdeals
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | * ** + = backOldPos coerce contract dimension element? generalPosition generators groebner groebner? groebnerIdeal ideal in? inRadical? intersect leadingIdeal quotient relationsIdeal saturate zeroDim?

Abbreviation: | PR
Full name: | PolynomialRing
Belongs to: | FiniteAbelianMonoidRing
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce content degree exquo ground ground? leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial map mapExponents minimumDegree monomial monomial? numberOfMonomials one? primitivePart recip reductum retract retractIfCan unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | POLY
Full name: | Polynomial
Belongs to: | PolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP content convert degree differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? integrate isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? patternMatch prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum resultant retract retractIfCan solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables zero?

Abbreviation: | PI
Full name: | PositiveInteger
Belongs to: | AbelianSemiGroup Monoid OrderedSet
Operations: | 1 * ** + < = coerce gcd max min one? recip

Abbreviation: | PF
Full name: | PrimeField
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo FiniteAlgebraicExtensionField FiniteFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = Frobenius algebraic? associates? basis characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP convert coordinates createNormalElement createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial degree dimension discreteLog divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean extensionDegree factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator inGroundField? index init inv lcm lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm normal? normalElement one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random recip rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace transcendenceDegree transcendent? unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | PRIMARR
Full name: | PrimitiveArray
Belongs to: | OneDimensionalArrayAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? coerce concat construct convert copy copyInto! count delete elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first index? indices insert less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? new parts position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates reverse reverse! select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? swap!

Abbreviation: | PRODUCT
Full name: | Product
Belongs to: | AbelianGroup AbelianMonoid CancellationAbelianMonoid Finite Group Monoid OrderedAbelianMonoidSup OrderedSet SetCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = coerce commutator conjugate index inv lookup makeprod max min one? random recip selectfirst selectsecond size sup zero?

Abbreviation: | QFORM
Full name: | QuadraticForm
Belongs to: | AbelianGroup
Operations: | 0 * + - = coerce elt matrix quadraticForm zero?

Abbreviation: | QALGSET
Full name: | QuasiAlgebraicSet
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce definingEquations definingInequation empty? idealSimplify quasiAlgebraicSet setStatus simplify

Abbreviation: | QUAT
Full name: | Quaternion
Belongs to: | QuaternionCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = D abs characteristic charthRoot coerce conjugate convert differentiate elt eval imagI imagJ imagK inv map max min norm one? quatern rational rational? rationalIfCan real recip reducedSystem retract retractIfCan zero?

Abbreviation: | QEQUAT
Full name: | QueryEquation
Belongs to: |
Operations: | equation value variable

Abbreviation: | QUEUE
Full name: | Queue
Belongs to: | QueueAggregate
Operations: | # = any? back bag coerce copy count dequeue! empty empty? enqueue! eq? every? extract! front insert! inspect length less? map map! member? members more? parts queue rotate! size?

Abbreviation: | RADFF
Full name: | RadicalFunctionField
Belongs to: | FunctionFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D absolutelyIrreducible? associates? basis branchPoint? branchPointAtInfinity? characteristic characteristicPolynomial charthRoot coerce complementaryBasis convert coordinates definingPolynomial derivationCoordinates differentiate discriminant divide elt euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor gcd generator genus integral? integralAtInfinity? integralBasis integralBasisAtInfinity integralCoordinates integralDerivationMatrix integralMatrix integralMatrixAtInfinity integralRepresents inv inverseIntegralMatrix inverseIntegralMatrixAtInfinity lcm lift minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nonSingularModel norm normalizeAtInfinity numberOfComponents one? prime? primitivePart principalIdeal quo ramified? ramifiedAtInfinity? rank rationalPoint? rationalPoints recip reduce reduceBasisAtInfinity reducedSystem regularRepresentation rem represents retract retractIfCan singular? singularAtInfinity? sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart trace traceMatrix unit? unitCanonical unitNormal yCoordinates zero?

Abbreviation: | RADIX
Full name: | RadixExpansion
Belongs to: | QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs associates? ceiling characteristic coerce convert cycleRagits denom denominator differentiate divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor floor fractRadix fractRagits fractionPart gcd init inv lcm map max min multiEuclidean negative? nextItem numer numerator one? patternMatch positive? prefixRagits prime? principalIdeal quo random recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan sign sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart wholeRadix wholeRagits zero?

Abbreviation: | RMATRIX
Full name: | RectangularMatrix
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo RectangularMatrixCategory VectorSpace
Operations: | 0 # * + - / = antisymmetric? any? coerce column copy count diagonal? dimension elt empty empty? eq? every? exquo less? listOfLists map map! matrix maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex more? ncols nrows nullSpace nullity parts qelt rank rectangularMatrix row rowEchelon size? square? symmetric? zero?

Abbreviation: | REF
Full name: | Reference
Belongs to: | Object SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce deref elt ref setelt setref

Abbreviation: | RULE
Full name: | RewriteRule
Belongs to: | Eltable RetractableTo SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce elt lhs pattern quotedOperators retract retractIfCan rhs rule suchThat

Abbreviation: | ROMAN
Full name: | RomanNumeral
Belongs to: | IntegerNumberSystem
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = D abs addmod associates? base binomial bit? characteristic coerce convert copy dec differentiate divide euclideanSize even? expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorial gcd hash inc init invmod lcm length mask max min mulmod multiEuclidean negative? nextItem odd? one? patternMatch permutation positive? positiveRemainder powmod prime? principalIdeal quo random rational rational? rationalIfCan recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan roman shift sign sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart submod symmetricRemainder unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | RULECOLD
Full name: | RuleCalled
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce name

Abbreviation: | RULESET
Full name: | Ruleset
Belongs to: | Eltable SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce elt rules ruleset

Abbreviation: | FORMULA1
Full name: | ScriptFormulaFormat1
Belongs to: | Object
Operations: | coerce

Abbreviation: | FORMULA
Full name: | ScriptFormulaFormat
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce convert display epilogue formula new prologue setEpilogue! setFormula! setPrologue!

Abbreviation: | SEGBIND
Full name: | SegmentBinding
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce equation segment variable

Abbreviation: | SEG
Full name: | Segment
Belongs to: | SegmentCategory SegmentExpansionCategory
Operations: | = BY SEGMENT coerce convert expand hi high incr lo low map segment

Abbreviation: | SCFRAC
Full name: | SemiCancelledFraction
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo QuotientFieldCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs associates? ceiling characteristic charthRoot coerce conditionP convert denom denominator differentiate divide elt euclideanSize eval expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial floor fractionPart gcd gcdPolynomial init inv lcm map max min multiEuclidean negative? nextItem normalize numer numerator one? patternMatch positive? prime? principalIdeal quo random recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan sign sizeLess? solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial unit? unitCanonical unitNormal wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | SDPOL
Full name: | SequentialDifferentialPolynomial
Belongs to: | DifferentialPolynomialCategory RetractableTo
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP content degree differentialVariables differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? initial isExpt isPlus isTimes isobaric? lcm leader leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable makeVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? order prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum resultant retract retractIfCan separant solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables weight weights zero?

Abbreviation: | SDVAR
Full name: | SequentialDifferentialVariable
Belongs to: | DifferentialVariableCategory
Operations: | < = D coerce differentiate makeVariable max min order retract retractIfCan variable weight

Abbreviation: | SET
Full name: | Set
Belongs to: | FiniteSetAggregate
Operations: | # < = any? bag brace cardinality coerce complement construct convert copy count dictionary difference empty empty? eq? every? extract! find index insert! inspect intersect less? lookup map map! max member? members min more? parts random reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates select select! size size? subset? symmetricDifference union universe

Abbreviation: | SEXOF
Full name: | SExpressionOf
Belongs to: | SExpressionCategory
Operations: | # = atom? car cdr coerce convert destruct elt eq expr float float? integer integer? list? null? pair? string string? symbol symbol? uequal

Abbreviation: | SEX
Full name: | SExpression
Belongs to: | SExpressionCategory
Operations: | # = atom? car cdr coerce convert destruct elt eq expr float float? integer integer? list? null? pair? string string? symbol symbol? uequal

Abbreviation: | SAE
Full name: | SimpleAlgebraicExtension
Belongs to: | MonogenicAlgebra
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D associates? basis characteristic characteristicPolynomial charthRoot coerce conditionP convert coordinates createPrimitiveElement definingPolynomial derivationCoordinates differentiate discreteLog discriminant divide euclideanSize expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorsOfCyclicGroupSize gcd generator index init inv lcm lift lookup minimalPolynomial multiEuclidean nextItem norm one? order prime? primeFrobenius primitive? primitiveElement principalIdeal quo random rank recip reduce reducedSystem regularRepresentation rem representationType represents retract retractIfCan size sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart tableForDiscreteLogarithm trace traceMatrix unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | SAOS
Full name: | SingletonAsOrderedSet
Belongs to: | OrderedSet
Operations: | < = coerce create max min

Abbreviation: | SINT
Full name: | SingleInteger
Belongs to: | IntegerNumberSystem
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - < = And D Not Or \^{} abs addmod and associates? base binomial bit? characteristic coerce convert copy dec differentiate divide euclideanSize even? expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorial gcd hash inc init invmod lcm length mask max min mulmod multiEuclidean negative? nextItem not odd? one? or patternMatch permutation positive? positiveRemainder powmod prime? principalIdeal quo random rational rational? rationalIfCan recip reducedSystem rem retract retractIfCan shift sign sizeLess? squareFree squareFreePart submod symmetricRemainder unit? unitCanonical unitNormal xor zero?

Abbreviation: | SMP
Full name: | SparseMultivariatePolynomial
Belongs to: | PolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce conditionP content convert degree differentiate discriminant eval exquo factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multivariate numberOfMonomials one? patternMatch prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart recip reducedSystem reductum resultant retract retractIfCan solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate variables zero?

Abbreviation: | SMTS
Full name: | SparseMultivariateTaylorSeries
Belongs to: | MultivariateTaylorSeriesCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh characteristic charthRoot coefficient coerce complete cos cosh cot coth csc csch csubst degree differentiate eval exp exquo extend fintegrate integrate leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial log map monomial monomial? nthRoot one? order pi pole? polynomial recip reductum sec sech sin sinh sqrt tan tanh unit? unitCanonical unitNormal variables zero?

Abbreviation: | STBL
Full name: | SparseTable
Belongs to: | TableAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce construct copy count dictionary elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert! inspect key? keys less? map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? parts qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates search select select! setelt size? swap! table

Abbreviation: | SUP
Full name: | SparseUnivariatePolynomial
Belongs to: | UnivariatePolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce composite conditionP content degree differentiate discriminant divide divideExponents elt euclideanSize eval expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? init integrate isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable makeSUP map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multiEuclidean multiplyExponents multivariate nextItem numberOfMonomials one? order outputForm prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart principalIdeal pseudoDivide pseudoQuotient pseudoRemainder quo recip reducedSystem reductum rem resultant retract retractIfCan separate sizeLess? solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial subResultantGcd totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate unmakeSUP variables vectorise zero?

Abbreviation: | SUTS
Full name: | SparseUnivariateTaylorSeries
Belongs to: | UnivariateTaylorSeriesCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch approximate asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh center characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce complete cos cosh cot coth csc csch degree differentiate elt eval exp exquo extend integrate leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial log map monomial monomial? multiplyCoefficients multiplyExponents nthRoot one? order pi pole? polynomial quoByVar recip reductum sec sech series sin sinh sqrt tan tanh terms truncate unit? unitCanonical unitNormal variable variables zero?

Abbreviation: | SQMATRIX
Full name: | SquareMatrix
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo SquareMatrixCategory
Operations: | 0 1 # * ** + - / = D antisymmetric? any? characteristic coerce column copy count determinant diagonal diagonal? diagonalMatrix diagonalProduct differentiate elt empty empty? eq? every? exquo inverse less? listOfLists map map! matrix maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex minordet more? ncols nrows nullSpace nullity one? parts qelt rank recip reducedSystem retract retractIfCan row rowEchelon scalarMatrix size? square? squareMatrix symmetric? trace transpose zero?

Abbreviation: | STACK
Full name: | Stack
Belongs to: | StackAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce copy count depth empty empty? eq? every? extract! insert! inspect less? map map! member? members more? parts pop! push! size? stack top

Abbreviation: | STREAM
Full name: | Stream
Belongs to: | LazyStreamAggregate
Operations: | # = any? child? children coerce complete concat concat! cons construct convert copy count cycleEntry cycleLength cycleSplit! cycleTail cyclic? delay delete distance elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? explicitEntries? explicitlyEmpty? explicitlyFinite? extend fill! filterUntil filterWhile find findCycle first frst generate index? indices insert last lazy? lazyEvaluate leaf? less? map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? new node? nodes numberOfComputedEntries output parts possiblyInfinite? qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates repeating repeating? rest rst second select setchildren! setelt setfirst! setlast! setrest! setvalue! showAll? showAllElements size? split! swap! tail third value

Abbreviation: | STRTBL
Full name: | StringTable
Belongs to: | TableAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce construct copy count dictionary elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert! inspect key? keys less? map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? parts qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates search select select! setelt size? swap! table

Abbreviation: | STRING
Full name: | String
Belongs to: | StringCategory
Operations: | # < = any? coerce concat construct copy copyInto! count delete elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first index? indices insert leftTrim less? lowerCase lowerCase! map map! match? max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? new parts position prefix? qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates replace reverse reverse! rightTrim select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? split string substring? suffix? swap! trim upperCase upperCase!

Abbreviation: | COMPPROP
Full name: | SubSpaceComponentProperty
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = close closed? coerce copy new solid solid?

Abbreviation: | SUBSPACE
Full name: | SubSpace
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = addPoint addPoint2 addPointLast birth child children closeComponent coerce deepCopy defineProperty extractClosed extractIndex extractPoint extractProperty internal? leaf? level merge modifyPoint new numberOfChildren parent pointData root? separate shallowCopy subspace traverse

Abbreviation: | SUCH
Full name: | SuchThat
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce construct lhs rhs

Abbreviation: | SYMBOL
Full name: | Symbol
Belongs to: | ConvertibleTo OrderedSet PatternMatchable
Operations: | < = argscript coerce convert elt list max min name new patternMatch resetNew script scripted? scripts string subscript superscript

Abbreviation: | SYMPOLY
Full name: | SymmetricPolynomial
Belongs to: | FiniteAbelianMonoidRing
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce content degree exquo ground ground? leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial map mapExponents minimumDegree monomial monomial? numberOfMonomials one? primitivePart recip reductum retract retractIfCan unit? unitCanonical unitNormal zero?

Abbreviation: | TABLEAU
Full name: | Tableau
Belongs to: | Object
Operations: | coerce listOfLists tableau

Abbreviation: | TABLE
Full name: | Table
Belongs to: | TableAggregate
Operations: | # = any? bag coerce construct copy count dictionary elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? extract! fill! find first index? indices insert! inspect key? keys less? map map! maxIndex member? members minIndex more? parts qelt qsetelt! reduce remove remove! removeDuplicates search select select! setelt size? swap! table

Abbreviation: | TS
Full name: | TaylorSeries
Belongs to: | MultivariateTaylorSeriesCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh characteristic charthRoot coefficient coerce complete cos cosh cot coth csc csch degree differentiate eval exp exquo extend fintegrate integrate leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial log map monomial monomial? nthRoot one? order pi pole? polynomial recip reductum sec sech sin sinh sqrt tan tanh unit? unitCanonical unitNormal variables zero?

Abbreviation: | TEX1
Full name: | TexFormat1
Belongs to: | Object
Operations: | coerce

Abbreviation: | TEX
Full name: | TexFormat
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce convert display epilogue new prologue setEpilogue! setPrologue! setTex! tex

Abbreviation: | TEXTFILE
Full name: | TextFile
Belongs to: | FileCategory
Operations: | = close! coerce endOfFile? iomode name open read! readIfCan! readLine! readLineIfCan! reopen! write! writeLine!

Abbreviation: | VIEW3D
Full name: | ThreeDimensionalViewport
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = axes clipSurface close coerce colorDef controlPanel diagonals dimensions drawStyle eyeDistance hitherPlane intensity key lighting makeViewport3D modifyPointData move options outlineRender perspective reset resize rotate showClipRegion showRegion subspace title translate viewDeltaXDefault viewDeltaYDefault viewPhiDefault viewThetaDefault viewZoomDefault viewpoint viewport3D write zoom

Abbreviation: | SPACE3
Full name: | ThreeSpace
Belongs to: | ThreeSpaceCategory
Operations: | = check closedCurve closedCurve? coerce components composite composites copy create3Space curve curve? enterPointData lllip lllp llprop lp lprop merge mesh mesh? modifyPointData numberOfComponents numberOfComposites objects point point? polygon polygon? subspace

Abbreviation: | TREE
Full name: | Tree
Belongs to: | RecursiveAggregate
Operations: | # = any? children coerce copy count cyclic? elt empty empty? eq? every? leaf? leaves less? map map! member? members more? node? nodes parts setchildren! setelt setvalue! size? tree value

Abbreviation: | TUBE
Full name: | TubePlot
Belongs to: |
Operations: | closed? getCurve listLoops open? setClosed tube

Abbreviation: | TUPLE
Full name: | Tuple
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce length select

Abbreviation: | ARRAY2
Full name: | TwoDimensionalArray
Belongs to: | TwoDimensionalArrayCategory
Operations: | # = any? coerce column copy count elt empty empty? eq? every? fill! less? map map! maxColIndex maxRowIndex member? members minColIndex minRowIndex more? ncols new nrows parts qelt qsetelt! row setColumn! setRow! setelt size?

Abbreviation: | VIEW2D
Full name: | TwoDimensionalViewport
Belongs to: | SetCategory
Operations: | = axes close coerce connect controlPanel dimensions getGraph graphState graphStates graphs key makeViewport2D move options points putGraph region reset resize scale show title translate units viewport2D write

Abbreviation: | ULSCONS
Full name: | UnivariateLaurentSeriesConstructor
Belongs to: | UnivariateLaurentSeriesConstructorCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D abs acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch approximate asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh ceiling center characteristic charthRoot coefficient coerce complete conditionP convert cos cosh cot coth csc csch degree denom denominator differentiate divide elt euclideanSize eval exp expressIdealMember exquo extend extendedEuclidean factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial floor fractionPart gcd gcdPolynomial init integrate inv laurent lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial log map max min monomial monomial? multiEuclidean multiplyCoefficients multiplyExponents negative? nextItem nthRoot numer numerator one? order patternMatch pi pole? positive? prime? principalIdeal quo random rationalFunction recip reducedSystem reductum rem removeZeroes retract retractIfCan sec sech series sign sin sinh sizeLess? solveLinearPolynomialEquation sqrt squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial tan tanh taylor taylorIfCan taylorRep terms truncate unit? unitCanonical unitNormal variable variables wholePart zero?

Abbreviation: | ULS
Full name: | UnivariateLaurentSeries
Belongs to: | UnivariateLaurentSeriesConstructorCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch approximate asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh center characteristic charthRoot coefficient coerce complete cos cosh cot coth csc csch degree denom denominator differentiate divide elt euclideanSize eval exp expressIdealMember exquo extend extendedEuclidean factor gcd integrate inv laurent lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial log map monomial monomial? multiEuclidean multiplyCoefficients multiplyExponents nthRoot numer numerator one? order pi pole? prime? principalIdeal quo rationalFunction recip reducedSystem reductum rem removeZeroes retract retractIfCan sec sech series sin sinh sizeLess? sqrt squareFree squareFreePart tan tanh taylor taylorIfCan taylorRep terms truncate unit? unitCanonical unitNormal variable variables zero?

Abbreviation: | UP
Full name: | UnivariatePolynomial
Belongs to: | UnivariatePolynomialCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / < = D associates? characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce composite conditionP content degree differentiate discriminant divide divideExponents elt euclideanSize eval expressIdealMember exquo extendedEuclidean factor factorPolynomial factorSquareFreePolynomial gcd gcdPolynomial ground ground? init integrate isExpt isPlus isTimes lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial mainVariable makeSUP map mapExponents max min minimumDegree monicDivide monomial monomial? monomials multiEuclidean multiplyExponents multivariate nextItem numberOfMonomials one? order prime? primitiveMonomials primitivePart principalIdeal pseudoDivide pseudoQuotient pseudoRemainder quo recip reducedSystem reductum rem resultant retract retractIfCan separate sizeLess? solveLinearPolynomialEquation squareFree squareFreePart squareFreePolynomial subResultantGcd totalDegree unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariate unmakeSUP variables vectorise zero?

Abbreviation: | UPXSCONS
Full name: | UnivariatePuiseuxSeriesConstructor
Belongs to: | UnivariatePuiseuxSeriesConstructorCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch approximate asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh center characteristic charthRoot coefficient coerce complete cos cosh cot coth csc csch degree differentiate divide elt euclideanSize eval exp expressIdealMember exquo extend extendedEuclidean factor gcd integrate inv laurent laurentIfCan laurentRep lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial log map monomial monomial? multiEuclidean multiplyExponents nthRoot one? order pi pole? prime? principalIdeal puiseux quo rationalPower recip reductum rem retract retractIfCan sec sech series sin sinh sizeLess? sqrt squareFree squareFreePart tan tanh terms truncate unit? unitCanonical unitNormal variable variables zero?

Abbreviation: | UPXS
Full name: | UnivariatePuiseuxSeries
Belongs to: | UnivariatePuiseuxSeriesConstructorCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch approximate asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh center characteristic charthRoot coefficient coerce complete cos cosh cot coth csc csch degree differentiate divide elt euclideanSize eval exp expressIdealMember exquo extend extendedEuclidean factor gcd integrate inv laurent laurentIfCan laurentRep lcm leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial log map monomial monomial? multiEuclidean multiplyExponents nthRoot one? order pi pole? prime? principalIdeal puiseux quo rationalPower recip reductum rem retract retractIfCan sec sech series sin sinh sizeLess? sqrt squareFree squareFreePart tan tanh terms truncate unit? unitCanonical unitNormal variable variables zero?

Abbreviation: | UTS
Full name: | UnivariateTaylorSeries
Belongs to: | UnivariateTaylorSeriesCategory
Operations: | 0 1 * ** + - / = D acos acosh acot acoth acsc acsch approximate asec asech asin asinh associates? atan atanh center characteristic charthRoot coefficient coefficients coerce complete cos cosh cot coth csc csch degree differentiate elt eval evenlambert exp exquo extend generalLambert integrate invmultisect lagrange lambert leadingCoefficient leadingMonomial log map monomial monomial? multiplyCoefficients multiplyExponents multisect nthRoot oddlambert one? order pi pole? polynomial quoByVar recip reductum revert sec sech series sin sinh sqrt tan tanh terms truncate unit? unitCanonical unitNormal univariatePolynomial variable variables zero?

Abbreviation: | UNISEG
Full name: | UniversalSegment
Belongs to: | SegmentCategory SegmentExpansionCategory
Operations: | = BY SEGMENT coerce convert expand hasHi hi high incr lo low map segment

Abbreviation: | VARIABLE
Full name: | Variable
Belongs to: | CoercibleTo SetCategory
Operations: | = coerce variable

Abbreviation: | VECTOR
Full name: | Vector
Belongs to: | VectorCategory
Operations: | # * + - < = any? coerce concat construct convert copy copyInto! count delete dot elt empty empty? entries entry? eq? every? fill! find first index? indices insert less? map map! max maxIndex member? members merge min minIndex more? new parts position qelt qsetelt! reduce remove removeDuplicates reverse reverse! select setelt size? sort sort! sorted? swap! vector zero

Abbreviation: | VOID
Full name: | Void
Belongs to: |
Operations: | coerce void

Book ContentsPrevious Section 17.1 Axiom CategoriesNext Section 19.1 Axiom PackagesBook Index